<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface-1">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>Maven is a build tool, a project management tool, an abstract
  container for running build tasks. It is a tool that has shown itself
  indispensable for projects that graduate beyond the simple and need to start
  finding consistent ways to manage and build large collections of
  interdependent modules and libraries which make use of tens or hundreds of
  third-party components. It is a tool that has removed much of the burden of
  3rd party dependency management from the daily work schedule of millions of
  engineers, and it has enabled many organizations to evolve beyond the toil
  and struggle of build management into a new phase where the effort required
  to build and maintain software is no longer a limiting factor in software
  design.</para>

  <para>This work is the first attempt at a comprehensive title on Maven. It
  builds upon the combined experience and work of the authors of all previous
  Maven titles, and you should view it not as a finished work but as the first
  edition in a long line of updates to follow. While Maven has been around for
  a few years, the authors of this book believe that it has just begun to
  deliver on the audacious promises it makes. The authors, and company behind
  this book, <ulink url="http://www.sonatype.com">Sonatype</ulink>, believe
  that the publishing of this book marks the beginning of a new phase of
  innovation and development surrounding Maven and the software ecosystem that
  surrounds it.</para>

  <section id="preface-1-sect-how-to-use">
    <title>How to Use this Book</title>

    <para>Pick it up, read some of the text on the pages. Once you reach the
    end of a page, you'll want to either click on a link if you are looking at
    the <acronym>HTML</acronym> version, or, if you have the printed book,
    you'll lift up a corner of a page and turn it. If you are sitting next to
    a computer, you can type in some of the examples and try to follow along.
    Please don't throw a book this large at anyone in anger.</para>

    <para>This book is divided into three parts: Introductory Material, <xref
    linkend="part-example" />, and <xref linkend="part-reference" />. The
    introductory material consists of two chapters: <xref
    linkend="introduction" /> and <xref linkend="installation" />. <xref
    linkend="part-example" /> introduces Maven by developing some real
    examples and walking you through the structure of those examples providing
    motivation and explanation along the way. If you are new to Maven, start
    with <xref linkend="part-example" />. <xref linkend="part-reference" /> is
    less introduction than reference. Each chapter in <xref
    linkend="part-reference" /> deals with a focused topic and dives into as
    much detail as possible about each topic. For example, the <xref
    linkend="writing-plugins" /> chapter in <xref linkend="part-reference" />
    deals with writing plugins by providing a few examples and a series of
    lists and tables.</para>

    <para>While both <xref linkend="part-example" /> and <xref
    linkend="part-reference" /> provide explanation, each part takes a
    different strategy. Where <xref linkend="part-example" /> focuses on the
    context of a Maven project, <xref linkend="part-reference" /> focuses on a
    single topic. You can skip around in the book, <xref
    linkend="part-example" /> is by no means a prerequisite for <xref
    linkend="part-reference" />, but you'll have a better appreciation for
    <xref linkend="part-reference" /> if you read through <xref
    linkend="part-example" />. Maven is best learned by example, but once
    you've gone through the examples, you are going to need a good reference
    to start customizing Maven for your own environment.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="preface-1-sect-feedback">
    <title>Your Feedback</title>

    <para>We didn't write this book so we could send off a Word document to
    our publisher and go to a launch party to congratulate ourselves on a job
    well done. This book isn't "done"; in fact, this book will never be
    completely "done". The subject it covers is constantly changing and
    expanding, and we consider this work an ongoing conversation with the
    community. Publishing the book means that the real work has just begun,
    and you, as a reader, play a pivotal role to helping to maintain and
    improve this book. If you see something in this book that is wrong: a
    spelling mistake, some bad code, a blatant lie, then you should tell us,
    send us an email at: <ulink
    url="mailto:tobrien@sonatype.com">book@sonatype.com</ulink>.</para>

    <!--TODO: Change this to mavenbook@sonatype.com when it is available.-->

    <para>The ongoing relevance of this book depends upon your feedback. We
    want to know what works and what doesn't work. We want to know if there is
    any information you couldn't understand. We especially want to know if you
    think that the book is awful. Positive or negative comments are all
    welcome. Of course, we reserve the right to disagree, but all feedback
    will be rewarded with a gracious response.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="preface-1-sect-fontConventions">
    <title>Font Conventions</title>

    <para>This book follows certain conventions for font usage. Understanding
    these conventions up-front makes it easier to use this book.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis
        role="italic"><literal>Italic</literal></emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for filenames, file extensions, URLs, application names,
          emphasis, and new terms when they are first introduced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal moreinfo="none">Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for Java class names, methods, variables, properties,
          data types, database elements, and snippets of code that appear in
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        bold</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for commands you enter at the command line and to
          highlight new code inserted in a running example.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="italic"> <literal moreinfo="none">Constant width
        italic</literal> </emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used to annotate output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="preface-1-sect-writing-conventions">
    <title>Maven Writing Conventions</title>

    <para>The book follows certain conventions for naming and font usage in
    relation to Apache Maven. Understanding these conventions up-front makes
    it easier to read this book.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compiler plugin</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maven plugins are capitalized.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>create</varname> goal</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maven goal names are displayed in a constant width
          font.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>"plugin"</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>While "plug-in" (with hyphen) would be the grammatically
          correct form, this book writes the term as "plugin" both because it
          is easier to read and write and because it is a standard throughout
          the Maven community.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maven Lifecycle, Maven Standard Directory Layout, Maven Plugin,
        Project Object Model</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Core Maven concepts are capitalized whenever they are being
          referenced in the text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>goalParameter</varname></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A Maven goal parameter is displayed in a constant width
          font.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>compile</varname> phase</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lifecycle phases are displayed in a constant width
          font.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="preface-1-sect-acknowledgements">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>Sonatype would like to thank the following contributors. The people
    listed below have provided feedback which has helped improve the quality
    of this book. Thanks to Raymond Toal, Steve Daly, Paul Strack, Paul
    Reinerfelt, Chad Gorshing, Marcus Biel, Brian Dols, Mangalaganesh
    Balasubramanian, Marius Kruger, and Mark Stewart. Special thanks to Joel
    Costigliola for helping to debug and correct the Spring web chapter. Stan
    Guillory was practically a contributing author given the number of
    corrections he posted to the book's Get Satisfaction. Thank you Stan.
    Special thanks to Richard Coasby of Bamboo for acting as the provisional
    grammar consultant.</para>

    <para>Thanks to our contributing authors including Eric Redmond.</para>

    <para>Thanks to the following contributors who reported errors either in
    an email or using the Get Satisfaction site: Paco Soberón, Ray Krueger,
    Steinar Cook, Henning Saul, Anders Hammar, "george_007", "ksangani", Niko
    Mahle, Arun Kumar, Harold Shinsato, "mimil", "-thrawn-", Matt Gumbley. If
    you see your Get Satisfaction username in this list, and you would like it
    replaced with your real name, send an email to <ulink
    url="mailto:book@sonatype.com">book@sonatype.com</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Special thanks to Grant Birchmeier for taking the time to proofread
    portions of the book and file extremely detailed feedback via
    GetSatisfaction.</para>
  </section>
</preface>
