<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix-pom-details">
  <title>Appendix: POM Details</title>

  <para>POM stands for "Project Object Model". It is an XML representation of
  a Maven project stored in a file named <filename>pom.xml</filename>. A
  project is much more than just source code and configuration, software
  projects are defined by the code, people, organizations, and systems
  involved in the day to day collaboration that creates software. The POM
  captures every aspect of a project. The POM encompasses concepts like
  configuration files, the developers involved, the defect tracking system,
  the organization, the licenses, the project's URL, the dependencies, and all
  of the other information involved in a project. In Maven, code is secondary
  to the POM; a project need not contain any code at all, simply a
  <filename>pom.xml</filename>.</para>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-intro">
    <title>POM Structure</title>

    <para>The following is a list of elements which can appear directly under
    a POM's <sgmltag>project</sgmltag> element.</para>

    <!--TODO: The separation of elements in the POM seems very arbitrary, why is dependencies in POM Relationships and not in the Build 
environment.  I'm following Eric's lead here, I wonder if I should.-->

    <para><example>
        <title>Top-level Elements of a Project Object Model (POM)</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;

  &lt;!-- POM Relationships --&gt;
  &lt;parent&gt;...&lt;/parent&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;...&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;...&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;...&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;modules&gt;...&lt;/modules&gt;
  &lt;dependencies&gt;...&lt;/dependencies&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;...&lt;/packaging&gt;

  &lt;!-- General Project Information --&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;...&lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;url&gt;...&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;inceptionYear&gt;...&lt;/inceptionYear&gt;
  &lt;licenses&gt;...&lt;/licenses&gt;
  &lt;organization&gt;...&lt;/organization&gt;
  &lt;developers&gt;...&lt;/developers&gt;
  &lt;contributors&gt;...&lt;/contributors&gt;

  &lt;!-- Build Settings --&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;...&lt;/build&gt;
  &lt;reporting&gt;...&lt;/reporting&gt;

  &lt;!-- Build Environment Settings --&gt;
  &lt;dependencyManagement&gt;...&lt;/dependencyManagement&gt;
  &lt;properties&gt;...&lt;/properties&gt;
  &lt;issueManagement&gt;...&lt;/issueManagement&gt;
  &lt;ciManagement&gt;...&lt;/ciManagement&gt;
  &lt;mailingLists&gt;...&lt;/mailingLists&gt; 
  &lt;scm&gt;...&lt;/scm&gt;
  &lt;prerequisites&gt;...&lt;/prerequisites&gt;
  &lt;repositories&gt;...&lt;/repositories&gt;
  &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;...&lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;...&lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  &lt;profiles&gt;...&lt;/profiles&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>Notice that <sgmltag>modelVersion</sgmltag> contains 4.0.0. When
    this book was written, this was the only supported POM version for Maven
    2. <sgmltag>modelVersion</sgmltag> is always required.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The Contents of a Project Object Model (POM)</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/pom-relationships_pom-small.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-xml-schema">
    <title>POM XML Schema</title>

    <para>The POM XSD is available at <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd">http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd</ulink>
    and the Settings XSD is available at <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/xsd/settings-1.0.0.xsd">http://maven.apache.org/xsd/settings-1.0.0.xsd</ulink>.
    They can be referenced in the POM by setting the &lt;project&gt; element
    like so:</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Namespace and XML Schema Location for pom.xml</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0
                             http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd"&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>And settings as such:</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Namespace and XML Schema Location for settings.xml</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;settings xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0
                              http://maven.apache.org/xsd/settings-1.0.0.xsd"&gt;
  ...
&lt;/settings&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>Finally, this <ulink
    url="http://sonatype.com/book/images/pom-details/pom-cheat-sheet.png">cheat
    sheet</ulink> may help you visualize the layout.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-basics">
    <title>The Basics</title>

    <para>The POM contains all necessary information about a project, as well
    as configurations of plugins to be used during the build process. It is,
    effectively, the declarative manifestation of the "who", "what", and
    "where", while the build lifecycle is the "when" and "how". That is not to
    say that the POM cannot affect the flow of the lifecycle  it can. For
    example, by configuring the maven-antrun-plugin, one can effectively embed
    ant tasks inside of the POM. It is ultimately a declaration, however.
    Where as a build.xml tells ant precisely what to do when it is run
    (procedural), a POM states its configuration (declarative). If some
    external force causes the lifecycle to skip the ant plugin execution, it
    will not stop the plugins that are executed from doing their magic. This
    is unlike a build.xml file, where tasks are almost always dependant on the
    lines executed before it.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Defining Maven Coordinates in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;my-project&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-coords">
      <title>Maven Coordinates</title>

      <para>The POM defined above is the minimum that Maven 2 will allow.
      groupId:artifactId:version are all required fields (although, groupId
      and version need not be explicitly defined if they are inherited from a
      parent  more on inheritance later). The three fields act much like an
      address and timestamp in one. This marks a specific place in a
      repository, acting like a coordinate system for Maven projects.</para>

      <para>* groupId: This is generally unique amongst an organization or a
      project. For example, all core Maven artifacts do (well, should) live
      under the groupId org.apache.maven. Group ID's do not necessarily use
      the dot notation, for example, the junit project. Note that the
      dot-notated groupId does not have to correspond to the package structure
      that the project contains. It is, however, a good practice to follow.
      When stored within a repository, the group acts much like the Java
      packaging structure does in an operating system. The dots are replaced
      by OS specific directory separators (such as / in Unix) which becomes
      a relative directory structure from the base repository. In the example
      given, the org.codehaus.mojo group lives within the directory
      $M2_REPO/org/codehaus/mojo.</para>

      <para>* artifactId: The artifactId is generally the name that the
      project is known by. Although the groupId is important, people within
      the group will rarely mention the groupId in discussion (they are often
      all be the same ID, such as the <ulink
      url="http://mojo.codehaus.org/">Codehaus Mojo</ulink> project groupId:
      org.codehaus.mojo). It, along with the groupId, create a key that
      separates this project from every other project in the world (at least,
      it should :) ). Along with the groupId, the artifactId fully defines the
      artifacts living quarters within the repository. In the case of the
      above project, my-project lives in
      $M2_REPO/org/codehaus/mojo/my-project.</para>

      <para>* version: This is the last piece of the naming puzzle.
      groupId:artifactId denote a single project but they cannot delineate
      which incarnation of that project we are talking about. Do we want the
      junit:junit of today (version 4), or of four years ago (version 2)? In
      short: code changes, those changes should be versioned, and this element
      keeps those versions in line. It is also used within an artifacts
      repository to separate versions from each other. my-project version 1.0
      files live in the directory structure
      $M2_REPO/org/codehaus/mojo/my-project/1.0.</para>

      <para>The three elements given above point to a specific version of a
      project letting Maven knows who we are dealing with, and when in its
      software lifecycle we want them.</para>

      <para>* packaging: Now that we have our address structure of
      groupId:artifactId:version, there is one more standard label to give us
      a really complete address. That is the project's artifact type. In our
      case, the example POM for org.codehaus.mojo:my-project:1.0 defined above
      will be packaged as a jar. We could make it into a war by declaring a
      different packaging:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring a Project for WAR Packaging</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;packaging&gt;war&lt;/packaging&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When no packaging is declared, Maven assumes the artifact is the
      default: jar. The valid types are Plexus role-hints (read more on Plexus
      for a explanation of roles and role-hints) of the component role
      org.apache.maven.lifecycle.mapping.LifecycleMapping. The current core
      packaging values are: pom, jar, maven-plugin, ejb, war, ear, rar, par.
      These define the default list of goals which execute to each
      corresponding build lifecycle stage for a particular package
      structure.</para>

      <para>You will sometimes see Maven print out a project coordinate as
      groupId:artifactId:packaging:version.</para>

      <para>* classifier: You may occasionally find a fifth element on the
      coordinate, and that is the classifier. We will visit the classifier
      later, but for now it suffices to know that those kinds of projects are
      displayed as groupId:artifactId:packaging:classifier:version.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-relationships">
      <title>POM Relationships</title>

      <para>One powerful aspect of Maven is in its handling of project
      relationships; that includes dependencies (and transitive dependencies),
      inheritance, and aggregation (multi-module projects). Dependency
      management has a long tradition of being a complicated mess for anything
      but the most trivial of projects. "Jarmageddon" quickly ensues as the
      dependency tree becomes large and complicated. "Jar Hell" follows, where
      versions of dependencies on one system are not equivalent to versions as
      those developed with, either by the wrong version given, or conflicting
      versions between similarly named jars. Maven solves both problems
      through a common local repository from which to link projects correctly,
      versions and all.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-dependencies">
      <title>Dependencies</title>

      <para>The cornerstone of the POM is its dependency list. Most every
      project depends upon others to build and run correctly, and if all Maven
      does for you is manage this list for you, you have gained a lot. Maven
      downloads and links the dependencies for you on compilation and other
      goals that require them. As an added bonus, Maven brings in the
      dependencies of those dependencies (transitive dependencies), allowing
      your list to focus solely on the dependencies your project
      requires.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Declaring Dependencies in a POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;junit&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;junit&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;4.0&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;type&gt;jar&lt;/type&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;test&lt;/scope&gt;
      &lt;classifier&gt;memory&lt;/classifier&gt;
      &lt;optional&gt;true&lt;/optional&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>groupId, artifactId, version—These elements are self-explanatory,
      and you will see them often. This trinity represents the coordinate of a
      specific project in time, demarcating it as a dependency of this
      project. You may be thinking: "This means that my project can only
      depend upon Maven artifacts!" The answer is, "Of course, but that's a
      good thing." This forces you to depend solely on dependencies that Maven
      can manage. There are times, unfortunately, when a project cannot be
      downloaded from the central Maven repository. For example, a project may
      depend upon a jar that has a closed-source license which prevents it
      from being in a central repository. There are three methods for dealing
      with this scenario.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Install the dependency locally using the install plugin. The
          method is the simplest recommended method. For example: <screen>
mvn install:install-file -Dfile=non-maven-proj.jar -DgroupId=some.group -DartifactId=non-maven-proj -Dversion=1
</screen></para>

          <note>
            <para>Notice that an address is still required, only this time you
            use the command line and the install plugin will create a POM for
            you with the given address.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create your own repository and deploy it there. This is a
          favorite method for companies with an intranet and need to be able
          to keep everyone in synch. There is a Maven goal called
          deploy:deploy-file which is similar to the install:install-file goal
          (read the plugin's goal page for more information).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the dependency scope to system and define a systemPath.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Using a systemPath is not recommended. but leads us to explaining
      the following elements:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Corresponds to the dependant artifact's packaging type. This
            defaults to jar. While it usually represents the extension on the
            filename of the dependency, that is not always the case. A type
            can be mapped to a different extension. Some examples are
            ejb-client and test-jar, whose extension is actually jar.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>scope</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This element refers to the classpath of the task at hand
            (compiling and runtime, testing, etc.) as well as how to limit the
            transitivity of a depedency. There are five scopes
            available:</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>compile</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>this is the default scope, used if none is specified.
                  Compile dependencies are available in all classpaths.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>provided</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>this is much like compile, but indicates you expect
                  the JDK or a container to provide it. It is only available
                  on the compilation classpath, and is not transitive.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>runtime</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>this scope indicates that the dependency is not
                  required for compilation, but is for execution. It is in the
                  runtime and test classpaths, but not the compile
                  classpath.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>test</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>this scope indicates that the dependency is not
                  required for normal use of the application, and is only
                  available for the test compilation and execution
                  phases.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>system</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>this scope is similar to provided except that you have
                  to provide the JAR which contains it explicitly. The
                  artifact is always available and is not looked up in a
                  repository.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>systemPath</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>is used only if the the dependency scope is system.
            Otherwise, the build will fail if this element is set. The path
            must be absolute, so it is recommended to use a property to
            specify the machine-specific path (more on properties below), such
            as \${java.home}/lib. Since it is assumed that system scope
            dependencies are installed a priori, Maven will not check the
            repositories for the project, but instead checks to ensure that
            the file exists. If not, Maven will fail the build and suggest
            that you download and install it manually.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>classifier</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is an optional fifth element to define the coordinate
            of a dependency that contains a classifier. Classifiers were
            briefly mentioned above, and will be covered in more detail
            below.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>optional</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Marks optional a dependency when this project itself is a
            dependency. Confused? For example, imagine a project A that
            depends upon project B to compile a portion of code that may not
            be used at runtime, then we may have no need for project B for all
            project. So if project X adds project A as its own dependency,
            then Maven will not need to install project B at all.
            Symbolically, if =&gt; represents a required dependency, and
            --&gt; represents optional, although A=&gt;B may be the case when
            building A X=&gt;A--&gt;B would be the case when building
            X.</para>

            <para>In the shortest terms, optional lets other projects know
            that, when you use this project, you do not require this
            dependency in order to work correctly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-exclusions">
      <title>Exclusions</title>

      <para>Exclusions explicitly tell Maven that you don't want to include
      the specified project that is a dependency of this dependency (in other
      words, its transitive dependency). For example, the maven-embedder
      requires maven-core, and we do not wish to use it or its dependencies,
      then we would add it as an exclusion.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring a Dependency Exclusion</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-embedder&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;exclusions&gt;
        &lt;exclusion&gt;
          &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven&lt;/groupId&gt;
          &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;/exclusion&gt;
      &lt;/exclusions&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>exclusions—Exclusions contain one or more exclusion elements, each
      containing a groupId and artifactId denoting a dependency to exclude.
      Unlike optional, which may or may not be installed and used, exclusions
      actively remove themselves from the dependency tree.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-inheritance">
      <title>Inheritance</title>

      <para>One powerful addition that Maven brings to build management is the
      concept of project inheritance. Although in build systems such as Ant,
      inheritance can certainly be simulated, Maven has gone the extra step in
      making project inheritance explicit to the project object model.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>A Parent POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;my-parent&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;pom&lt;/packaging&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>The packaging type required to be pom for parent and aggregation
      (multi-module) projects. These types define the goals bound to a set of
      lifecycle stages. For example, if packaging is jar, then the package
      phase will execute the jar:jar goal. If the packaging is pom, the goal
      executed will be site:attach-descriptor. Now we may add values to the
      parent POM, which will be inherited by its children. The elements in the
      parent POM that are inherited by its children are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>dependencies</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>developers and contributors</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>plugin lists</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>reports lists</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>plugin executions with matching ids</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>plugin configuration</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><example>
          <title>Project Inheritance in a Child POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;parent&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;my-parent&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;relativePath&gt;../my-parent&lt;/relativePath&gt;
  &lt;/parent&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;my-project&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Notice the relativePath element. It is not required, but may be
      used as a signifier to Maven to first search the path given for this
      project's parent, before searching the local and then remote
      repositories.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-super-pom">
    <title>The Super POM</title>

    <para>Similar to the inheritance of objects in object oriented
    programming, POMs that extend a parent POM inherit certain values from
    that parent. Moreover, just as Java objects ultimately inherit from
    java.lang.Object, all Project Object Models inherit from a base Super
    POM.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>The Super POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;Maven Default Project&lt;/name&gt;

  &lt;repositories&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;central&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Maven Repository Switchboard&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;layout&gt;default&lt;/layout&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;snapshots&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;false&lt;/enabled&gt;
      &lt;/snapshots&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
  &lt;/repositories&gt;

  &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;
    &lt;pluginRepository&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;central&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Maven Plugin Repository&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;layout&gt;default&lt;/layout&gt;
      &lt;snapshots&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;false&lt;/enabled&gt;
      &lt;/snapshots&gt;
      &lt;releases&gt;
        &lt;updatePolicy&gt;never&lt;/updatePolicy&gt;
      &lt;/releases&gt;
    &lt;/pluginRepository&gt;
  &lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;

  &lt;build&gt;
    &lt;directory&gt;target&lt;/directory&gt;
    &lt;outputDirectory&gt;target/classes&lt;/outputDirectory&gt;
    &lt;finalName&gt;\${artifactId}-\${version}&lt;/finalName&gt;
    &lt;testOutputDirectory&gt;target/test-classes&lt;/testOutputDirectory&gt;
    &lt;sourceDirectory&gt;src/main/java&lt;/sourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;scriptSourceDirectory&gt;src/main/scripts&lt;/scriptSourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;testSourceDirectory&gt;src/test/java&lt;/testSourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;resources&gt;
      &lt;resource&gt;
        &lt;directory&gt;src/main/resources&lt;/directory&gt;
      &lt;/resource&gt;
    &lt;/resources&gt;
    &lt;testResources&gt;
      &lt;testResource&gt;
        &lt;directory&gt;src/test/resources&lt;/directory&gt;
      &lt;/testResource&gt;
    &lt;/testResources&gt;
  &lt;/build&gt;

  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;outputDirectory&gt;target/site&lt;/outputDirectory&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;

  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;release-profile&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;activation&gt;
        &lt;property&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;performRelease&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;/activation&gt;

      &lt;build&gt;
        &lt;plugins&gt;
          &lt;plugin&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-source-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;executions&gt;
              &lt;execution&gt;
                &lt;id&gt;attach-sources&lt;/id&gt;
                &lt;goals&gt;
                  &lt;goal&gt;jar&lt;/goal&gt;
                &lt;/goals&gt;
              &lt;/execution&gt;
            &lt;/executions&gt;
          &lt;/plugin&gt;

          &lt;plugin&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-javadoc-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;executions&gt;
              &lt;execution&gt;
                &lt;id&gt;attach-javadocs&lt;/id&gt;
                &lt;goals&gt;
                  &lt;goal&gt;jar&lt;/goal&gt;
                &lt;/goals&gt;
              &lt;/execution&gt;
            &lt;/executions&gt;
          &lt;/plugin&gt;

          &lt;plugin&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-deploy-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;configuration&gt;
              &lt;updateReleaseInfo&gt;true&lt;/updateReleaseInfo&gt;
            &lt;/configuration&gt;
          &lt;/plugin&gt;
        &lt;/plugins&gt;
      &lt;/build&gt;
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;

&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>You can take a look at how the Super POM affects your Project Object
    Model by creating a minimal pom.xml and executing on the command line: mvn
    help:effective-pom</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-depman">
    <title>Dependency Management</title>

    <para>Besides inheriting certain top-level elements, parents have elements
    to configure values for child POMs that do not affect the parents own
    build lifecycle. One of those elements is dependencyManagement.</para>

    <para>* dependencyManagement: is used only by parent POMs to help manage
    dependency information across all of its children. If the my-parent
    project uses dependencyManagement to define a dependency on
    junit:junit:4.0, then POMs inheriting from this one can set their
    dependency giving the groupId=junit and artifactId=junit only, then Maven
    will fill in the version set by the parent. The benefits of this method
    are obvious. Dependency details can be set in one central location, which
    will propagate to all inheriting POMs.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-aggreg">
    <title>Aggregation (or Multi-Module)</title>

    <para>A project with modules is known as a multimodule, or aggregator
    project. Modules are projects that this POM lists, and are executed as a
    group. An pom packaged project may aggregate the build of a set of
    projects by listing them as modules, which are relative directories to
    those projects.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Defining Project Modules in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;my-parent&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;modules&gt;
    &lt;module&gt;my-project&lt;module&gt;
  &lt;/modules&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>A final note on Inheritance vs. Aggregation: Inheritance and
    aggregation create a nice dynamic to control builds through a single,
    high-level POM. You will often see projects that are both parents and
    aggregators. For example, the entire maven core runs through a single base
    POM org.apache.maven:maven, so building the Maven project can be executed
    by a single command: mvn compile. However, although both POM projects, an
    aggregator project and a parent project are not one in the same and should
    not be confused. A POM project may be inherited from - but does not
    necessarily have - any modules that it aggregates. Conversely, a POM
    project may aggregate projects that do not inherit from it.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-props">
    <title>Properties</title>

    <para>Properties are the last required piece in understanding POM basics.
    Maven properties are value placeholder, like properties in Ant. Their
    values are accessible anywhere within a POM by using the notation $\{X\},
    where X is the property. They come in five different styles:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>env.X: Prefixing a variable with "env." will return the shells
        environment variable. For example, $\{env.PATH\} contains the $path
        environment variable (%PATH% in Windows). </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>project.x: A dot (.) notated path in the POM will contain the
        corresponding elements value. For example:
        &lt;project&gt;&lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;&lt;/project&gt; is
        accessible via $\{project.version\}. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>settings.x: A dot (.) notated path in the settings.xml will
        contain the corresponding elements value. For example:
        &lt;settings&gt;&lt;offline&gt;false&lt;/offline&gt;&lt;/settings&gt;
        is accessible via $\{settings.offline\}. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Java System Properties: All properties accessible via
        java.lang.System.getProperties() are available as POM properties, such
        as $\{java.home\}. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>x: Set within a &lt;properties /&gt; element or an external
        files, the value may be used as $\{someVar\}.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-build">
    <title>Build Settings</title>

    <para>Beyond the basics of the POM given above, there are two more
    elements that must be understood before claiming basic competency of the
    POM. They are the build element, that handles things like declaring your
    project's directory structure and managing plugins; and the reporting
    element, that largely mirrors the build element for reporting
    purposes.</para>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-build-element">
      <title>Build</title>

      <para>According to the POM 4.0.0 XSD, the build element is conceptually
      divided into two parts: there is a BaseBuild type which contains the set
      of elements common to both build elements (the top-level build element
      under project and the build element under profiles, covered below); and
      there is the Build type, which contains the BaseBuild set as well as
      more elements for the top level definition. Let us begin with an
      analysis of the common elements between the two.</para>

      <note>
        <para>These different build elements may be denoted "project build"
        and "profile build".</para>
      </note>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Build Settings in POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;!-- "Project Build" contains more elements than just the BaseBuild set --&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;...&lt;/build&gt;

  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;!-- "Profile Build" contains a subset of "Project Build"s elements --&gt;
      &lt;build&gt;...&lt;/build&gt;
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-basebuild">
      <title>The BaseBuild Element Set</title>

      <para>BaseBuild is exactly as it sounds: the base set of elements
      between the two build elements in the POM.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Top-level Elements in Build Configuration</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;build&gt;
  &lt;defaultGoal&gt;install&lt;/defaultGoal&gt;
  &lt;directory&gt;\${basedir}/target&lt;/directory&gt;
  &lt;finalName&gt;\${artifactId}-\${version}&lt;/finalName&gt;
  &lt;filters&gt;
    &lt;filter&gt;filters/filter1.properties&lt;/filter&gt;
  &lt;/filters&gt;
  ...
&lt;/build&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para><variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>defaultGoal</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>the default goal or phase to execute if none is given. If
              a goal is given, it should be defined as it is in the command
              line (such as jar:jar). The same goes for if a phase is defined
              (such as install). </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>directory</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is the directory where the build will dump its files
              or, in Maven parlance, the build's target. It aptly defaults to
              \${basedir}/target. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>finalName</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is the name of the bundled project when it is finally
              built (sans the file extension, for example:
              my-project-1.0.jar). It defaults to \${artifactId}-\${version}.
              The term "finalName" is kind of a misnomer, however, as plugins
              that build the bundled project have every right to ignore/modify
              this name (but they usually do not). For example, if the
              maven-jar-plugin is configured to give a jar a classifier of
              test, then the actual jar defined above will be built as
              my-project-1.0-test.jar. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>filter</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Defines *.properties files that contain a list of
              properties that apply to resources which accept their settings
              (covered below). In other words, the "name=value" pairs defined
              within the filter files replace $\{name\} strings within
              resources on build. The example above defines the
              filter1.properties file under the filter/ directory. Mavens
              default filter directory is $\{basedir\}/src/main/filters</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <section id="appendix-pom-sect-resources">
        <title>Resources</title>

        <para>Another feature of build elements is specifying where resources
        exist within your project. Resources are not (usually) code. They are
        not compiled, but are items meant to be bundled within your project or
        used for various other reasons, such as code generation.</para>

        <para>For example, a Plexus project requires a configuration.xml file
        (which specifies component configurations to the container) to live
        within the META-INF/plexus directory. Although we could just as easily
        place this file within src/main/resource/META-INF/plexus, we want
        instead to give Plexus its own directory of src/main/plexus. In order
        for the JAR plugin to bundle the resource correctly, you would specify
        resources similar to the following:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring Resources in a POM</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    ...
    &lt;resources&gt;
      &lt;resource&gt;
        &lt;targetPath&gt;META-INF/plexus&lt;/targetPath&gt;
        &lt;filtering&gt;false&lt;/filtering&gt;
        &lt;directory&gt;\${basedir}/src/main/plexus&lt;/directory&gt;
        &lt;includes&gt;
          &lt;include&gt;configuration.xml&lt;/include&gt;
        &lt;/includes&gt;
        &lt;excludes&gt;
          &lt;exclude&gt;**/*.properties&lt;/exclude&gt;
        &lt;/excludes&gt;
      &lt;/resource&gt;
    &lt;/resources&gt;
    &lt;testResources&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/testResources&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para><variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>resources</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>is a list of resource elements that each describe what
                and where to include files associated with this
                project.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>targetPath</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the directory structure to place the set of
                resources from a build. Target path defaults to the base
                directory. A commonly specified target path for resources that
                will be packaged in a JAR is META-INF.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>filtering</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>is true or false, denoting if filtering is to be enabled
                for this resource. Note, that filter *.properties files do not
                have to be defined for filtering to occur  resources can also
                use properties that are by default defined in the POM (such as
                \${project.version}), passed into the command line using the
                "-D" flag (for example, "-Dname=value") or are explicitly
                defined by the properties element. Filter files were covered
                above.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>directory</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This element's value defines where the resources are to
                be found. The default directory for a build is
                \${basedir}/src/main/resources.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>includes</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A set of files patterns which specify the files to
                include as resources under that specified directory, using *
                as a wildcard.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>excludes</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The same structure as includes, but specifies which
                files to ignore. In conflicts between include and exclude,
                exclude wins.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>testResources</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The testResources element block contains testResource
                elements. Their definitions are similar to resource elements,
                but are naturally used during test phases. The one difference
                is that the default (Super POM defined) test resource
                directory for a project is $\{basedir\}/src/test/resources.
                Test resources are not deployed.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </section>

      <section id="appendix-pom-sect-plugins">
        <title>Plugins</title>

        <para><example>
            <title>Plugin Configuration in a POM</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    ...
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-jar-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;extensions&gt;false&lt;/extensions&gt;
        &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;classifier&gt;test&lt;/classifier&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
        &lt;dependencies&gt;...&lt;/dependencies&gt;
        &lt;executions&gt;...&lt;/executions&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>Beyond the standard coordinate of groupId:artifactId:version,
        there are elements which configure the plugin or this builds
        interaction with it.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>extensions</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>true or false, whether or not to load extensions of this
              plugin. It is by default false. Extensions are covered later in
              this document.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>inherited</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>true or false, whether or not this plugin configuration
              should apply to POMs which inherit from this one.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>configuration</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is specific to the individual plugin. Without going
              too in depth into the mechanics of how plugins work, suffice it
              to say that whatever properties that the plugin Mojo may expect
              (these are getters and setters in the Java Mojo bean) can be
              specified here. In the above example, we are setting the
              classifier property to test in the maven-jar-plugin's Mojo. It
              may be good to note that all configuration elements, wherever
              they are within the POM, are intended to pass values to another
              underlying system, such as a plugin. In other words: values
              within a configuration element are never explicitly required by
              the POM schema, but a plugin goal has every right to require
              configuration values.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>dependencies</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Dependencies are seen a lot within the POM, and are an
              element under all plugins element blocks. The dependencies have
              the same structure and function as under that base build. The
              major difference in this case is that instead of applying as
              dependencies of the project, they now apply as dependencies of
              the plugin that they are under. The power of this is to alter
              the dependency list of a plugin, perhaps by removing an unused
              runtime dependency via exclusions, or by altering the version of
              a required dpendency. See above under Dependencies for more
              information.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>executions</term>

            <listitem>
              <para> It is important to keep in mind that a plugin may have
              multiple goals. Each goal may have a separate configuration,
              possibly even binding a plugin's goal to a different phase
              altogether. executions configure the execution of a plugins
              goals.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>For example, suppose you wanted to bind the anrun:run goal to
        the verify phase. We want the task to echo the build directory, as
        well as avoid passing on this configuration to its children (assuming
        it is a parent) by setting inherited to false. You would get an
        execution like this:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring an Execution in Plugin Configuration</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;build&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-antrun-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;

        &lt;executions&gt;
          &lt;execution&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;echodir&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;goals&gt;
              &lt;goal&gt;run&lt;/goal&gt;
            &lt;/goals&gt;
            &lt;phase&gt;verify&lt;/phase&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;false&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;configuration&gt;
              &lt;tasks&gt;
                &lt;echo&gt;Build Dir: \${project.build.directory}&lt;/echo&gt;
              &lt;/tasks&gt;
            &lt;/configuration&gt;
          &lt;/execution&gt;
        &lt;/executions&gt;

      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para><variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>id</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Self explanatory. It specifies this execution block
                between all of the others. When the phase is run, it will be
                shown in the form: [plugin:goal {execution: id}]. In the case
                of this example: [antrun:run {execution: echodir}]</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>goals</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Like all pluralized POM elements, this contains a list
                of singular elements. In this case, a list of plugin goals
                which are being specified by this execution block.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>phase</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the phase that the list of goals will execute
                in. This is a very powerful option, allowing one to bind any
                goal to any phase in the build lifecycle, altering the default
                behavior of Maven.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>inherited</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Like the inherited element above, setting this false
                will supress Maven from passing this execution onto its
                children. This element is only meaningful to parent
                POMs.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>configuration</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Same as above, but confines the configuration to this
                specific list of goals, rather than all goals under the
                plugin.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </section>

      <section id="appendix-pom-sect-plugman">
        <title>Plugin Management</title>

        <para>pluginManagement is an element that is seen along side plugins.
        Plugin Management contains plugin elements in much the same way,
        except that rather than configuring plugin information for this
        particular project build, it is intended to configure project builds
        that inherit from this one. However, this only configures plugins that
        are actually referenced within the plugins element in the children.
        The children have every right to override pluginManagement
        definitions.</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Plugin Management in a POM's Build Configuration</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    ...
    &lt;pluginManagement&gt;
      &lt;plugins&gt;
        &lt;plugin&gt;
          &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
          &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-jar-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
          &lt;version&gt;2.0&lt;/version&gt;
          &lt;executions&gt;
            &lt;execution&gt;
              &lt;id&gt;pre-process-classes&lt;/id&gt;
              &lt;phase&gt;compile&lt;/phase&gt;
              &lt;goals&gt;
                &lt;goal&gt;jar&lt;/goal&gt;
              &lt;/goals&gt;
              &lt;configuration&gt;
                &lt;classifier&gt;pre-process&lt;/classifier&gt;
              &lt;/configuration&gt;
            &lt;/execution&gt;
          &lt;/executions&gt;
        &lt;/plugin&gt;
      &lt;/plugins&gt;
    &lt;/pluginManagement&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>If we added these specifications to the plugins element, they
        would apply only to a single POM. However, if we apply them under the
        pluginManagement element, then this POM and all inheriting POMs that
        add the maven-jar-plugin to the build will get the pre-process-classes
        execution as well. So rather than the above mess included in every
        child pom.xml, only the following is required:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Adding a Plugin to a Parent POM</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    ...
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-jar-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-build-element-set">
      <title>The Build Element Set</title>

      <para>The Build type in the XSD denotes those elements that are
      available only for the "project build". Despite the number of extra
      elements (six), there are really only two groups of elements that
      project build contains that are missing from the profile build:
      directories and extensions.</para>

      <section id="appendix-pom-sect-basebuild-dirs">
        <title>Directories</title>

        <para>The set of directory elements live in the parent build element,
        which set various directory structures for the POM as a whole. Since
        they do not exist in profile builds, these cannot be altered by
        profiles.</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring Directories in Build Configuration</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    &lt;sourceDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/src/main/java&lt;/sourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;scriptSourceDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/src/main/scripts&lt;/scriptSourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;testSourceDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/src/test/java&lt;/testSourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;outputDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/target/classes&lt;/outputDirectory&gt;
    &lt;testOutputDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/target/test-classes&lt;/testOutputDirectory&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>If the values of a *Directory element above is set as an
        absolute path (when their properties are expanded) then that directory
        is used. Otherwise, it is relative to the base build directory:
        $\{basedir\}.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="appendix-pom-sect-extensions">
        <title>Extensions</title>

        <para>Extensions are a list of artifacts that are to be used in this
        build. They will be included in the running build's classpath. They
        can enable extensions to the build process (such as add an ftp
        provider for the Wagon transport mechanism), as well as make plugins
        active which make changes to the build lifecycle. In short, extensions
        are artifacts that activated during build. The extensions do not have
        to actually do anything nor contain a Mojo. For this reason,
        extensions are excellent for specifying one out of multiple
        implementations of a common plugin interface.</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Declaring Extensions in Build Configuration</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    ...
    &lt;extensions&gt;
      &lt;extension&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.wagon&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;wagon-ftp&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;1.0-alpha-3&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;/extension&gt;
    &lt;/extensions&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</programlisting>
          </example></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-reporting">
    <title>Reporting</title>

    <para>Reporting contains the elements that correspond specifically for the
    site generation phase. Certain Maven plugins can generate reports defined
    and configured under the reporting element, for example: generating
    Javadoc reports. Much like the build element's ability to configure
    plugins, reporting commands the same ability. The glaring difference is
    that rather than fine-grained control of plug-in goals within the
    executions block, reporting configures goals within reportSet elements.
    And the subtler difference is that a plugin configuration under the
    reporting element works as build plugin configuration, although the
    opposite is not true (a build plugin configuration does not affect a
    reporting plugin).</para>

    <para>Possibly the only item under the reporting element that would not be
    familiar to someone who understood the build element is the Boolean
    excludeDefaults element. This element signifies to the site generator to
    exclude reports normally generated by default. When a site is generated
    via the site build cycle, a Project Info section is placed in the
    left-hand menu, chock full of reports, such as the Project Team report or
    Dependencies list report. These report goals are generated by
    maven-project-info-reports-plugin. Being a plugin like any other, it may
    also be suppressed in the following, more verbose, way, which effectively
    turns off project-info reports.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Reporting in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;outputDirectory&gt;\${basedir}/target/site&lt;/outputDirectory&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-project-info-reports-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;reportSets&gt;
          &lt;reportSet&gt;&lt;/reportSet&gt;
        &lt;/reportSets&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>The other difference is the outputDirectory element under plugin. In
    the case of reporting, the output directory is \${basedir}/target/site by
    default.</para>

    <para>It is important to keep in mind that an individual plugin may have
    multiple goals. Each goal may have a separate configuration. Report sets
    configure execution of a report plugins goals. Does this sound familiar 
    deja-vu? The same thing was said about builds execution element with one
    difference: you cannot bind a report to another phase. Sorry.</para>

    <para>For example, suppose you wanted to configure the javadoc:javadoc
    goal to link to "http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/", but only the
    javadoc goal (not the goal maven-javadoc-plugin:jar). We would also like
    this configuration passed to its children, and set inherited to true. The
    reportSet would resemble the following:</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Properties for a Report Set</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        ...
        &lt;reportSets&gt;
          &lt;reportSet&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;sunlink&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;reports&gt;
              &lt;report&gt;javadoc&lt;/report&gt;
            &lt;/reports&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;configuration&gt;
              &lt;links&gt;
                &lt;link&gt;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/&lt;/link&gt;
              &lt;/links&gt;
            &lt;/configuration&gt;
          &lt;/reportSet&gt;
        &lt;/reportSets&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>Between build executions and reporting reportSets, it should be
    clear now as to why they exist. In the simplest sense, they drill down in
    configuration. The POM must have a way not only to configure plugins, but
    they also must configure individual goals of those plugins. That is where
    these elements come in, giving the POM ultimate granularity in control of
    its build destiny.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-project-info">
    <title>More Project Information</title>

    <para>Although the above information is enough to get a firm grasp on POM
    authoring, there are far more elements to make developer's live easier.
    Many of these elements are related to site generation, but like all POM
    declarations, they may be used for anything, depending upon how certain
    plugins use it. The following are the simplest elements:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>name</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Projects tend to have conversational names, beyond the
          artifactId. The Sun engineers did not refer to their project as
          "java-1.5", but rather just called it "Tiger". Here is where to set
          that value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>description</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Description of a project is always good. Although this should
          not replace formal documentation, a quick comment to any readers of
          the POM is always helpful.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>url</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The URL, like the name, is not required. This is a nice
          gesture for projects users, however, so that they know where the
          project lives.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>inceptionYear</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This is another good documentation point. It will at least
          help you remember where you have spent the last few years of your
          life.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-licenses">
    <title>Licenses</title>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Licenses in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;licenses&gt;
  &lt;license&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Apache 2&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.txt&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;distribution&gt;repo&lt;/distribution&gt;
    &lt;comments&gt;A business-friendly OSS license&lt;/comments&gt;
  &lt;/license&gt;
&lt;/licenses&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>Licenses are legal documents defining how and when a project (or
    parts of a project) may be used. Note that a project should list only
    licenses that may apply directly to this project, and not list licenses
    that apply to this project's dependencies. Maven currently does little
    with these documents other than displays them on generated sites. However,
    there is talk of flexing for different types of licenses, forcing users to
    accept license agreements for certain types of (non open source)
    projects.</para>

    <para>name, url and comments: are self explanatory, and have been
    encountered before in other capacities. The fourth license element is:
    distribution: This describes how the project may be legally distributed.
    The two stated methods are repo (they may be downloaded from a Maven
    repository) or manual (they must be manually installed).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-organization">
    <title>Organization</title>

    <para>Most projects are run by some sort of organization (business,
    private group, etc.). Here is where the most basic information is
    set.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Organizations in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;organization&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Codehaus Mojo&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://mojo.codehaus.org&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/organization&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-developers">
    <title>Developers</title>

    <para>All projects consist of files that were created, at some time, by a
    person. Like the other systems that surround a project, so to do the
    people involved with a project have a stake in the project. Developers are
    presumably members of the project's core development. Note that, although
    an organization may have many developers (programmers) as members, it is
    not good form to list them all as developers, but only those who are
    immediately responsible for the code. A good rule of thumb is, if the
    person should not be contacted about the project, they need not be listed
    here.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Listing Developers in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;developers&gt;
    &lt;developer&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;eric&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Eric&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;eredmond@codehaus.org&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://eric.propellors.net&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;organization&gt;Codehaus&lt;/organization&gt;
      &lt;organizationUrl&gt;http://mojo.codehaus.org&lt;/organizationUrl&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;architect&lt;/role&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;developer&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;-6&lt;/timezone&gt;
      &lt;properties&gt;
        &lt;picUrl&gt;http://tinyurl.com/prv4t&lt;/picUrl&gt;
      &lt;/properties&gt;
    &lt;/developer&gt;
  &lt;/developers&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para><variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>id, name, email</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>These correspond to the developer's ID (presumably some
            unique ID across an organization), the developer's name and email
            address.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>organization, organizationUrl</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>As you probably guessed, these are the developer's
            organization name and it's URL, respectively.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>roles</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A role should specify the standard actions that the person
            is responsible for. Like a single person can wear many hats, a
            single person can take on multiple roles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>timezone</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A numerical offset in hours from GMT where the developer
            lives.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>properties</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This element is where any other properties about the person
            goes. For example, a link to a personal image or an instant
            messenger handle. Different plugins may use these properties, or
            they may simply be for other developers who read the POM.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-contributors">
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <para>Contributors are like developers yet play an ancillary role in a
    project's lifecycle. Perhaps the contributor sent in a bug fix, or added
    some important documentation. A healthy open source project will likely
    have more contributors than developers.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Listing Contributors in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;contributors&gt;
    &lt;contributor&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Noelle&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;some.name@gmail.com&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://noellemarie.com&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;organization&gt;Noelle Marie&lt;/organization&gt;
      &lt;organizationUrl&gt;http://noellemarie.com&lt;/organizationUrl&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;tester&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;-5&lt;/timezone&gt;
      &lt;properties&gt;
        &lt;gtalk&gt;some.name@gmail.com&lt;/gtalk&gt;
      &lt;/properties&gt;
    &lt;/contributor&gt;
  &lt;/contributors&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>Contributors contain the same set of elements than developers sans
    the id element.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-issue-man">
    <title>Issue Management</title>

    <para>This defines the defect tracking system (Bugzilla, TestTrack,
    ClearQuest, etc) used. Although there is nothing stopping a plugin from
    using this information for something, its primarily used for generating
    project documentation.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Declaring an Issue Management System in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;issueManagement&gt;
    &lt;system&gt;Bugzilla&lt;/system&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://127.0.0.1/bugzilla&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/issueManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-contint">
    <title>Continuous Integration</title>

    <para>Continuous integration build systems based upon triggers or timings
    (such as, hourly or daily) have grown in favor over manual builds in the
    past few years. As build systems have become more standardized, so have
    the systems that run the trigger those builds. Although the majority of
    the configuration is up to the specific program used (Hudson, Cruise
    Control, etc.), there are a few configurations which may take place within
    the POM. Maven has captured a few of the recurring settings within the set
    of notifier elements. A notifier is the manner in which people are
    notified of certain build statuses. In the following example, this POM is
    setting a notifier of type mail (meaning email), and configuring the email
    address to use on the specified triggers sendOnError, sendOnFailure, and
    not sendOnSuccess or sendOnWarning.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Continuous Integration in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;ciManagement&gt;
    &lt;system&gt;hudson&lt;/system&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://127.0.0.1:8080/hudson&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;notifiers&gt;
      &lt;notifier&gt;
        &lt;type&gt;mail&lt;/type&gt;
        &lt;sendOnError&gt;true&lt;/sendOnError&gt;
        &lt;sendOnFailure&gt;true&lt;/sendOnFailure&gt;
        &lt;sendOnSuccess&gt;false&lt;/sendOnSuccess&gt;
        &lt;sendOnWarning&gt;false&lt;/sendOnWarning&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;&lt;address&gt;hudson@127.0.0.1&lt;/address&gt;&lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/notifier&gt;
    &lt;/notifiers&gt;
  &lt;/ciManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-mailing-list">
    <title>Mailing Lists</title>

    <para>Mailing lists are a great tool for keeping in touch with people
    about a project. Most mailing lists are for developers and users.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Describing Project Mailing Lists in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;mailingLists&gt;
    &lt;mailingList&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;User List&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;subscribe&gt;user-subscribe@127.0.0.1&lt;/subscribe&gt;
      &lt;unsubscribe&gt;user-unsubscribe@127.0.0.1&lt;/unsubscribe&gt;
      &lt;post&gt;user@127.0.0.1&lt;/post&gt;
      &lt;archive&gt;http://127.0.0.1/user/&lt;/archive&gt;
      &lt;otherArchives&gt;
        &lt;otherArchive&gt;http://base.google.com/base/1/127.0.0.1&lt;/otherArchive&gt;
      &lt;/otherArchives&gt;
    &lt;/mailingList&gt;
  &lt;/mailingLists&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para><variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>subscribe, unsubscribe</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>There elements specify the email addresses which are used
            for performing the relative actions To subscribe to the user list
            above, a user would send an email to
            user-subscribe@127.0.0.1.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>archive</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This element specifies the url of the archive of old mailing
            list emails, if one exists. If there are mirrored archives, they
            can be specified under otherArchives.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>post</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The email address which one would use in order to post to
            the mailing list. Note that not all mailing lists have the ability
            to post to (such as a build failure list).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-config-man">
    <title>Software Configuration Management</title>

    <para>SCM (Software Configuration Management, also called Source
    Code/Control Management or, succinctly, version control) is an integral
    part of any healthy project. If your Maven project uses an SCM system (it
    does, doesn't it?) then here is where you would place that information
    into the POM.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Descrbing Source Control in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;scm&gt;
    &lt;connection&gt;scm:svn:http://127.0.0.1/svn/my-project&lt;/connection&gt;
    &lt;developerConnection&gt;scm:svn:https://127.0.0.1/svn/my-project&lt;/developerConnection&gt;
    &lt;tag&gt;HEAD&lt;/tag&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://127.0.0.1/websvn/my-project&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/scm&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>connection, developerConnection: The two connection elements convey
    to how one is to connect to the version control system through Maven.
    Where connection requires read access for Maven to be able to find the
    source code (for example, an update), developerConnection requires a
    connection that will give write access. The Maven project has spawned
    another project named Maven SCM, which creates a common API for any SCMs
    that wish to implement it. The most popular are CVS and Subversion,
    however, there is a growing list of other supported
    {{{/scm/scms-overview.html}SCMs}}. All SCM connections are made through a
    common URL structure.</para>

    <screen>scm:[provider]:[provider_specific]
</screen>

    <para>Where provider is the type of SCM system. For example, connecting to
    a CVS repository may look like this:</para>

    <screen>scm:cvs:pserver:127.0.0.1:/cvs/root:my-project
</screen>

    <para>tag: Specifies the tag that this project lives under. HEAD (meaning,
    the SCM root) should be the default.</para>

    <para>url: A publicly browsable repository. For example, via
    ViewCVS.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-prereqs">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para><example>
        <title>Declaring a Prerequisite for a Project</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;prerequisites&gt;
    &lt;maven&gt;2.0.4&lt;/maven&gt;
  &lt;/prerequisites&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>prerequisites: The POM may have certain prerequisites in order to
    execute correctly. For example, perhaps there was a fix in Maven 2.0.3
    that you need in order to deploy using sftp. Here is where you give the
    prerequisites to building. If these are not met, Maven will fail the build
    before even starting. The only element that exists as a prerequisite in
    POM 4.0 is the maven element, which takes a minimum version number</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-repos">
    <title>Repositories</title>

    <para>Repositories are collections of artifacts which adhere to the Maven
    repository directory layout. In order to be a Maven 2 repository artifact,
    a POM file must live within the structure
    $BASE_REPO/groupId/artifactId/version/artifactId-version.pom. $BASE_REPO
    can be local (file structure) or remote (base URL); the remaining layout
    will be the same. Repositories exist as a place to collect and store
    artifacts. Whenever a project has a dependency upon an artifact, Maven
    will first attempt to use a local copy of the specified artifact. If that
    artifact does not exist in the local repository, it will then attempt to
    download from a remote repository. The repository elements within a POM
    specify those alternate repositories to search.</para>

    <para>The repository is one of the most powerful features of the Maven
    community. The default central Maven repository lives on
    {{http://repo1.maven.org/maven2}}. Another source for artifacts not yet in
    iBiblio is the Codehaus snapshots repo.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Repositories in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;repositories&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;releases&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;false&lt;/enabled&gt;
        &lt;updatePolicy&gt;always&lt;/updatePolicy&gt;
        &lt;checksumPolicy&gt;warn&lt;/checksumPolicy&gt;
      &lt;/releases&gt;
      &lt;snapshots&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
        &lt;updatePolicy&gt;never&lt;/updatePolicy&gt;
        &lt;checksumPolicy&gt;fail&lt;/checksumPolicy&gt;
      &lt;/snapshots&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;codehausSnapshots&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Codehaus Snapshots&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://snapshots.maven.codehaus.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;layout&gt;default&lt;/layout&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
  &lt;/repositories&gt;
  &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para>releases, snapshots: These are the policies for each type of
    artifact, Release or snapshot. With these two sets, a POM has the power to
    alter the policies for each type independent of the other within a single
    repository. For example, one may decide to enable only snapshot downloads,
    possibly for development purposes.</para>

    <para>enabled: true or false for whether this repository is enabled for
    the respective type (releases or snapshots).</para>

    <para>updatePolicy: This element specifies how often updates should
    attempt to occur. Maven will compare the local POMs timestamp (stored in
    a repositorys maven-metadata file) to the remote. The choices are:
    always, daily (default), interval:X (where X is an integer in minutes) or
    never.</para>

    <para>checksumPolicy: When Maven deploys files to the repository, it also
    deploys corresponding checksum files. Your options are to ignore, fail, or
    warn on missing or incorrect checksums.</para>

    <para>layout: In the above description of repositories, it was mentioned
    that they all follow a common layout. This is mostly correct. Maven 2 has
    a default layout for its repositories; however, Maven 1.x had a different
    layout. Use this element to specify which if it is default or
    legacy.</para>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-plug-repos">
      <title>Plugin Repositories</title>

      <para>Repositories are home to two major types of artifacts. The first
      are artifacts that are used as dependencies of other artifacts. These
      are the majority of plugins that reside within central. The other type
      of artifact is plugins. Maven plugins are themselves a special type of
      artifact. Because of this, plugin repositories may be separated from
      other repositories (although, I have yet to hear a convincing argument
      for doing so). In any case, the structure of the pluginRepositories
      element block is similar to the repositories element. The
      pluginRepository elements each specify a remote location of where Maven
      can find new plugins</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-distman">
    <title>Distribution Management</title>

    <para>Distribution management acts precisely as it sounds: it manages the
    distribution of the artifact and supporting files generated throughout the
    build process. Starting with the last elements first:</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Distribution Management in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    ...
    &lt;downloadUrl&gt;http://mojo.codehaus.org/my-project&lt;/downloadUrl&gt;
    &lt;status&gt;deployed&lt;/status&gt;
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <para><variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>downloadUrl</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>is the url of the repository from whence another POM may
            point to in order to grab this POMs artifact. In the simplest
            terms, we told the POM how to upload it (through repository/url),
            but from where can the public download it? This element answers
            that question.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>status</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Warning! Like a baby bird in a nest, the status should never
            be touched by human hands! The reason for this is that Maven will
            set the status of the project when it is transported out to the
            repository. Its valid types are as follows.</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>none</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>No special status. This is the default for a
                  POM.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>converted</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The manager of the repository converted this POM from
                  an earlier version to Maven 2.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>partner</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>This could just as easily have been called synched.
                  This means that this artifact has been synched with a
                  partner repository.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>deployed</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>By far the most common status, meaning that this
                  artifact was deployed from a Maven 2 instance. This is what
                  you get when you manually deploy using the command-line
                  deploy phase.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>verified</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>This project has been verified, and should be
                  considered finalized.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-repository">
      <title>Repository</title>

      <para>Where as the repositories element specifies in the POM the
      location and manner in which Maven may download remote artifacts for use
      by the current project, distributionManagement specifies where (and how)
      this project will get to a remote repository when it is deployed. The
      repository elements will be used for snapshot distribution if the
      snapshotRepository is not defined.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Distribution Repositories in a POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;uniqueVersion&gt;false&lt;/uniqueVersion&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;corp1&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Corporate Repository&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;scp://repo1/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;layout&gt;default&lt;/layout&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
    &lt;snapshotRepository&gt;
      &lt;uniqueVersion&gt;true&lt;/uniqueVersion&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;propSnap&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Propellors Snapshots&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;sftp://propellers.net/maven&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;layout&gt;legacy&lt;/layout&gt;
    &lt;/snapshotRepository&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para><variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>id, name</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The id is used to uniquely identify this repository
              amongst many, and the name is a human readable form.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>uniqueVersion</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The unique version takes a true or false value to denote
              whether artifacts deployed to this repository should get a
              uniquely generated version number, or use the version number
              defined as part of the address.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>url</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is the core of the repository element. It specifies
              both the location and the transport protocol to be used to
              transfer a built artifact (and POM file, and checksum data) to
              the repository.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>layout</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>These are the same types and purpose as the layout element
              defined in the repository element. They are default and
              legacy.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-site-dist">
      <title>Site Distribution</title>

      <para>More than distribution to the repositories, distributionManagement
      is responsible for defining how to deploy the projects site and
      documentation.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Site Distribution in a POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    ...
    &lt;site&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;mojo.website&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Mojo Website&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;scp://beaver.codehaus.org/home/projects/mojo/public_html/&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;/site&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>id, name, url: These elements are similar to their counterparts
      above in the distributionManagement repository element.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-relocation">
      <title>Relocation</title>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Relocation in a POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    ...
    &lt;relocation&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;my-project&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;We have moved the Project under Apache&lt;/message&gt;
    &lt;/relocation&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Projects are not static; they are living things (or dying things,
      as the case may be). A common thing that happens as projects grow, is
      that they are forced to move to more suitable quarters. For example,
      when your next wildly successful open source project moves under the
      Apache umbrella, it would be good to give your users as heads-up that
      the project is being renamed to org.apache:my-project:1.0. Besides
      specifying the new address, it is also good form to provide a message
      explaining why.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-profiles">
    <title>Profiles</title>

    <para>A new feature of the POM 4.0 is the ability of a project to change
    settings depending on the environment where it is being built. A profile
    element contains both an optional activation (a profile trigger) and the
    set of changes to be made to the POM if that profile has been activated.
    For example, a project built for a test environment may point to a
    different database than that of the final deployment. Or dependencies may
    be pulled from different repositories based upon the JDK version used. The
    elements of profiles are as follows:</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Configuring Profiles in a POM</title>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;test&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;activation&gt;...&lt;/activation&gt;
      &lt;build&gt;...&lt;/build&gt;
      &lt;modules&gt;...&lt;/modules&gt;
      &lt;repositories&gt;...&lt;/repositories&gt;
      &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;...&lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;
      &lt;dependencies&gt;...&lt;/dependencies&gt;
      &lt;reporting&gt;...&lt;/reporting&gt;
      &lt;dependencyManagement&gt;...&lt;/dependencyManagement&gt;
      &lt;distributionManagement&gt;...&lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example></para>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-activation">
      <title>Activation</title>

      <para>Activations are the key of a profile. The power of a profile comes
      from its ability to modify the basic POM only under certain
      circumstances. Those circumstances are specified via an activation
      element.</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Profile Activation in a POM</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;test&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;activation&gt;
        &lt;activeByDefault&gt;false&lt;/activeByDefault&gt;
        &lt;jdk&gt;1.5&lt;/jdk&gt;
        &lt;os&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;Windows XP&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;family&gt;Windows&lt;/family&gt;
          &lt;arch&gt;x86&lt;/arch&gt;
          &lt;version&gt;5.1.2600&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/os&gt;
        &lt;property&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;mavenVersion&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;2.0.3&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;file&gt;
          &lt;exists&gt;\${basedir}/file2.properties&lt;/exists&gt;
          &lt;missing&gt;\${basedir}/file1.properties&lt;/missing&gt;
        &lt;/file&gt;
      &lt;/activation&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Activation occurs when all specified criteria have been met,
      though not all are required at once.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>jdk</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Activation has a built in, Java-centric check in the jdk
            element. This will activate if the test is run under a jdk version
            number that matches the prefix given. In the above example,
            1.5.0_06 will match.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>os</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The os element can define some operating system specific
            properties shown above.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>property</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The profile will activate if Maven detects a property (a
            value which can be dereferenced within the POM by \${name}) of the
            corresponding name=value pair.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>file</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Finally, a given filename may activate the profile by the
            existence of a file, or if it is missing.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The activation element is not the only way that a profile may be
      activated. The settings.xml file's activeProfile element may contain the
      profile's id. They may also be activated explicitly through the command
      line via a comma separated list after the P flag (e.g. -P test).</para>

      <para>To see which profile will activate in a certain build, use the
      maven-help-plugin.</para>

      <screen>mvn help:active-profiles
</screen>
    </section>

    <section id="appendix-pom-sect-basebuild-revisited">
      <title>The BaseBuild Element Set (revisited)</title>

      <para>As mentioned above, the reason for the two types of build elements
      reside in the fact that it does not make sense for a profile to
      configure build directories or extensions as it does in the top level of
      the POM. Reguardless of in which environment the project is built, some
      values will remain constant, such as the directory structure of the
      source code.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you find your project needing to keep two sets of code for
        different environments, it may be prudent to investigate refactoring
        the project into two or more separate projects.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="appendix-pom-sect-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>The Maven 2 POM is big. However, its size is also a testament to its
    versatility. The ability to abstract all of the aspects of a project into
    a single artifact is powerful, to say the least. Gone are the days of
    dozens of disparate build scripts and scattered documentation concerning
    each individual project. Along with Maven's other stars that make up the
    Maven galaxy a well defined build lifecycle, easy to write and maintain
    plugins, centralized repositories, system-wide and user-based
    configurations, as well as the increasing number of tools to make
    developers jobs easier to maintain complex projects the POM is the large,
    but bright, center.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
