<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="preface-copyright" role="copyrightpg">
  <title>Copyright</title>

  <para>Copyright 2008 Sonatype, Inc.</para>

  <para>Online version published by Sonatype, Inc., 654 High Street, Suite
  220, Palo Alto, CA, 94301.</para>

  <para>Print version published by O'Reilly Media, Inc., 1005 Gravenstein
  Highway North, Sebastopol, CA 95472.</para>

  <para>Nutshell Handbook, the Nutshell Handbook logo, and the O'Reilly logo
  are registered trademarks of O'Reilly Media, Inc. The <emphasis>Developer's
  Notebook</emphasis> series designations, the look of a laboratory notebook,
  and related trade dress are trademarks of O'Reilly Media, Inc.</para>

  <para>Java(TM) and all Java-based trademarks and logos are trademarks or
  registered trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc., in the United States and
  other countries. Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers
  to distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those
  designations appear in this book, and Sonatype, Inc. was aware of a
  trademark claim, the designations have been printed in caps or initial
  caps.</para>

  <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
  the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions,
  or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained
  herein.</para>

  <section id="preface-copyright-sect-creative-commons">
    <title>Creative Commons BY-ND-NC</title>

    <para>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons
    Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 United States license.
    For more information about this license, see <ulink
    url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/</ulink>.
    You are free to share, copy, distribute, display, and perform the work
    under the following conditions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You must attribute the work to Sonatype, Inc. with a link to
        <ulink
        url="http://www.sonatype.com">http://www.sonatype.com</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you redistribute this work on a web page, you must include the
    following link with the URL in the about attribute listed on a single line
    (remove the backslashes and join all URL parameters):</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;div xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" 
     about="http://creativecommons.org/license/results-one?q_1=2&amp;q_1=1\
            &amp;field_commercial=n&amp;field_derivatives=n&amp;field_jurisdiction=us\
            &amp;field_format=StillImage&amp;field_worktitle=Maven%3A+\Guide\
            &amp;field_attribute_to_name=Sonatype%2C+Inc.\
            &amp;field_attribute_to_url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.sonatype.com\
            &amp;field_sourceurl=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.sonatype.com%2Fbook\
            &amp;lang=en_US&amp;language=en_US&amp;n_questions=3"&gt;
   &lt;a rel="cc:attributionURL" property="cc:attributionName" 
      href="http://www.sonatype.com"&gt;Sonatype, Inc.&lt;/a&gt; / 
   &lt;a rel="license" 
         href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/"&gt;
     CC BY-NC-ND 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>When downloaded or distributed in a jurisdiction other than the
    United States of America, this work shall be covered by the appropriate
    ported version of Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative
    Works 3.0 license for the specific jurisdiction. If the Creative Commons
    Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works version 3.0 license is not
    available for a specific jurisdiction, this work shall be covered under
    the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivate Works version
    2.5 license for the jurisdiction in which the work was downloaded or
    distributed. A comprehensive list of jurisdictions for which a Creative
    Commons license is available can be found on the Creative Commons
    International web site at <ulink
    url="http://creativecommons.org/international">http://creativecommons.org/international</ulink>.</para>

    <para>If no ported version of the Creative Commons license exists for a
    particular jurisdiction, this work shall be covered by the generic,
    unported Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works
    version 3.0 license available from <ulink
    url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
</preface>
