<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="public-forward">
  <title>Foreword: ${project.version}</title>

  <para>Q. Wait, the book was sent to the printers and ink was applied to dead
  trees, but the book is still in Beta? What does this mean?</para>

  <para>A. It means that we're in this for the long haul. If we've been
  working on this book for the better part of the year and we're only on Beta
  ${project.version}, it means that we're still working to realize our vision
  of an ideal book. Expect a steady stream of improvements and additions to
  the book over the coming months.</para>

  <para>Q. Will we ever emerge from this book's Beta?</para>

  <para>A. Maybe not. Remember, GMail is still in Beta. If this book moves out
  of Beta, we're essentially saying that there is no more content to add and
  nothing is going to change. I've always thought that good books evolve over
  time and that they live beyond the confines of the chapters and sections
  that define them. A good book is an ongoing conversation and a series of
  interactions not just between authors and readers, but of lateral
  interactions between readers. That was a fancy way of saying that the book
  is a community.</para>

  <para>We've published a book with O'Reilly that will (to use a cliche)
  "stand the test of time". The printed version of this book contains
  information that will remain relevant and accurate going forward, and we
  encourage everyone to go out and purchase a book today. Even if you don't
  need it for yourself, you should go to Amazon, purchase a copy and give it
  to a friend who hasn't discovered Maven.</para>

  <para>Q. What's new in this version?</para>

  <para>Well, in this version, we separated the Nexus chapter into a
  stand-alone book. If you go to the Repository Management chapter, you'll see
  that it is a place-holder page and a link to a new, full book on Sonatype
  Nexus entitled <ulink url="${nexus.book.baseurl}">Repository Management with
  Nexus</ulink>.</para>

  <para>We've had some great feedback so far, please keep it coming. Your
  feedback is greatly appreciated, send it to <ulink
  url="mailto:book@sonatype.com">book@sonatype.com</ulink>. To keep yourself
  informed of updates, read the book blog at: <ulink
  url="http://blogs.sonatype.com/book">http://blogs.sonatype.com/book</ulink>.
  Everyone at Sonatype has had a hand in this version of the book, so the
  author is officially "Sonatype".</para>

  <para>Tim O'Brien (tobrien@sonatype.com)</para>

  <para>Evanston, IL</para>

  <para>January 16, 2008</para>

  <para>PS: Did I mention that you really should <ulink
  url="http://www.amazon.com/Maven-Definitive-Guide-Sonatype-Company/dp/0596517335/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1223866448&amp;sr=8-1">purchase
  a copy of this book</ulink>?</para>
</preface>