<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="reporting">
  <title>Reporting</title>

  <para>EARLY DRAFT</para>

  <para>This chapter follows an example project. You may wish to download the
  <ulink
  url="http://www.sonatype.com/book/examples/book-reporting.zip">reporting
  examples</ulink> and follow along.</para>

  <section id="reporting-sect-refresher">
    <title>A Quick Refresher: Building and Viewing a Project Website</title>

    <para>Before we get into the meat of this chapter, it's important to
    review the steps necessary to create a simple example project, then build
    and view its generated website. If you already know this part (we covered
    this in the Site Generation chapter), feel free to skip ahead.</para>

    <section id="reporting-sect-bootstrap">
      <title>Bootstrap Revisited: Hello-World</title>

      <para>Before we can configure project reports, we'll need a project. For
      this, we'll turn back to the handy hello-world example used in the Site
      Generation chapter. If you haven't read this chapter, or didn't follow
      along by creating your own hello-world project, you can get started with
      a quick Maven command:</para>

      <screen>workdir$ mvn archetype:create -DgroupId=book.reporting -DartifactId=hello-world
</screen>

      <note>
        <para>We're not creating the hello-world project from the
        maven-archetype-site or maven-archetype-site-simple archetypes.
        Although this would give us a good start at a project website, we
        really need some source code from which to generate things like
        unit-test reports. Maven will generate a basic website for any
        project, so we'll use the default archetype instead.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-build-it-view-it">
      <title>Build it, View it</title>

      <para>To generate the project website for our hello-world project,
      simply issue the following Maven command:</para>

      <screen>workdir$ cd hello-world
hello-world$ mvn clean site:run
</screen>

      <para>Initially, the clean step won't do anything. However, cleaning a
      project before you issue a build (or site) command is a good habit to
      get into, to avoid unpredictable results. Once you run the command
      above, you should be able to load the project website into your browser
      by going to http://localhost:8080. To stop the server, you'll need to
      press CTL-C in the console window. In the text below, when I say
      "regenerate and refresh" this site:run command -- coupled with a refresh
      of the browser window -- is what I'm referring to.</para>

      <para>Also, note that in some cases it may not be possible to preview
      the project website using the site:run mojo, due to a bug in its
      implementation. This is a known problem, described in the JIRA issue
      <ulink
      url="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/MSITE-220">MSITE-220</ulink>, and
      it leaves us with little alternative but to generate the site and load
      the HTML page straight off the filesystem. In these cases, you will need
      to direct your browser to open the corresponding path within the
      target/site/ sub-directory, under your hello-world project directory. I
      will give a clear indication when this is necessary.</para>

      <note>
        <para>This bug only affects the site:run mojo, not website generation
        in general. Rest assured that when you deploy your project's website,
        all configured reports will be included.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>As we saw in the Site Generation chapter, Maven can do much more
    than simply build and manage your project binaries; it can also help you
    manage your project's web presence. While it's critical to provide
    documentation to your community in the form of how-to's, feature lists,
    and other user-friendly formats, it's no less important to provide the
    community with some mechanism for assessing the health of the project
    itself. These mechanisms may include static code-analysis results,
    statistics on tests run against the project source code (unit,
    integration, and other types), along with any number of other reports.
    While it is possible to provide these reports to your community manually,
    this is an extremely time-consuming and tedious process that involves
    manually compiling statistics from the various output created by the build
    process, such as unit-test reports. These reports are critical for the
    user community, but they represent an unreasonable burden on developers;
    at least, as long as they are maintained manually.</para>

    <para>Much like the build process itself, the process of creating project
    reports cries out for automation. It is precisely this sort of automation
    that Maven can provide.</para>

    <para>A key over-arching goal of Maven is to make it easy for developers
    to do the right thing for their project and community. To that end, Maven
    provides a wealth of options for rendering these project-status reports
    into XHTML during the website-generation process, thereby automating an
    otherwise arduous and difficult process.</para>

    <para>To make the best use of Maven for project reporting, you'll need to
    understand two key configurations:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>configuration for Maven's project-info reports ( in the
        maven-project-info-reports-plugin plugin)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>configuration of other, additional project reports</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>We'll begin by exploring the configuration necessary to flesh out
    the project-info reports that are run by default when Maven generates a
    project website. Then, we'll discuss the basics of configuring additional
    project reports. Finally, we'll take a look at some of the most common and
    useful reports available at the Apache Maven and Codehaus Mojo projects,
    among other places.</para>

    <section id="reporting-sect-project-info">
      <title>Configuring Project-Info Reports</title>

      <para>By default, Maven generats a project website that contains several
      links, all under the heading of Project Information. However, if we
      don't add the right information to your project's POM, these pages will
      remain basically empty. These reports are the defaults because the Maven
      development team believes they are critical for giving relevant feedback
      about a project, and thus sustaining a healthy community around that
      project. So, to avoid offering false hope to users by way of these
      links, we should make sure they're up and running. For simplicity, we'll
      explore the project-info reports in the order that they appear in the
      default project website.</para>

      <para>Now, it's time to start customizing our example a little bit. The
      first thing any self-respecting project website needs is a declaration
      of the project's name and what it does, in simple terms (we'll leave the
      details for later). When the project website doesn't supply its own,
      custom index page, this role is filled by the About report. We'll start
      by configuring this report, then move on to provide some other standard
      information that every project should supply for its community.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-about-hello-world">
      <title>About (Hello-World)</title>

      <para>We can configure the About report to provide the user with some
      basic information about our hello-world project by setting the name and
      description elements in the POM, as follows:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title></title>

          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;name&gt;Hello, World&lt;/name&gt;
  ...
  &lt;description&gt;
    This project is a sample to help explain how project-website generation can be handled by Maven.
  &lt;/description&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <warning>
        <para>It seems that Maven's project-info-reports plugin currently
        doesn't handle HTML embedded in the POM description element very
        elegantly. In fact, putting HTML into the description haphazardly will
        cause the build to fail, with Maven complaining that it cannot parse
        the POM. If you take a more wily approach, and wrap the description
        content in a CDATA section, it will simply escape the HTML, and pass
        it on through...resulting in HTML markup that's visible on your
        project's front page. If you find yourself in this predicament,
        consider writing your own front page for the project, as described in
        the Site Generation chapter.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>[figs/reporting-about.png] Regenerate and refresh the project
      website and you will see this</para>

      <para>Now that we have a simple project description composed, we can
      direct attention to the other project reports (the project description
      is actually part of the About report). As you scan through the other
      project reports listed in the site navigation, it should become apparent
      just how little project information is presented here. We'll fix that
      next by adding some more information to the POM.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-continuous-integration">
      <title>Continuous Integration</title>

      <para>Your projects are all built in a continuous integration (CI)
      environment, so you can know immediately when someone breaks the
      codebase...right?</para>

      <para>By supplying the information for the project's CI environment, we
      give our developers (and users) an easy way to view up-to-date CI
      results. The key part of the POM for this is the ciManagement section.
      At a minimum, we should supply the type of our CI system and its URL, so
      users can find it:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title></title>

          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;project&gt;
  ...  
  &lt;ciManagement&gt;
    &lt;system&gt;hudson&lt;/system&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://dev.example.com/hudson&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/ciManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>This time, when you regenerate the project website and click on
      the Continuous Integration link, you should see two key items:</para>

      <para>[[1]] The project uses Hudson as its CI system.</para>

      <para>[[2]] The CI system for this project can be found at
      http://dev.example.com/hudson (and there's a link to this address on
      the page).</para>

      <para>So now, users and developers will be able to go to our project
      website and follow a link from there to the continuous integration
      system that has up-to-date build results for our project. But...is there
      more we could do? For example, how does our CI server let developers
      know of build failures? If the project gets a new developer, how would
      this developer subscribe for CI notifications? Clearly, we need to
      provide a little more information in the ciManagement section:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title></title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;ciManagement&gt;
    ...
    &lt;notifiers&gt;
      &lt;notifier&gt;
        &lt;type&gt;mail&lt;/type&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;address&gt;hello-world-notifications@dev.example.com&lt;/address&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/notifier&gt;
    &lt;/notifiers&gt;
  &lt;/ciManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When you regenerate and refresh, you should see the notifications
      email address show up under the Notifiers section, giving users the
      final piece of information necessary to track CI builds for our
      project.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-dependencies">
      <title>Dependencies</title>

      <para>Most projects have dependencies on other libraries or applications
      that are developed externally. The Dependencies report simply gives our
      community a view into what libraries the project depends on, and for
      what. As you know, Maven has five dependency scopes - compile, test,
      runtime, provided, and the strange (and hopefully, soon-to-be
      deprecated) system. This report will calculate the complete dependency
      set (including dependencies of our dependencies, and so on) for each of
      these scopes, and maps out where in the dependency hierarchy each one
      was found.</para>

      <para>For our hello-world project, this report is quite simplistic,
      containing only the single junit dependency. The JUnit jar has no
      dependencies of its own, and JUnit itself is only a test-scope
      dependency for our project - which means it won't be needed by users
      declaring a dependency on our project. This means our dependency report
      is pretty short and uninteresting. To illustrate the power of the
      Dependencies report, let's add another dependency to the POM:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuing a Project's Dependencies</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-project&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.0.4&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;    
    ...
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Regenerate the site, refresh your browser, and take another look.
      This time, you should see a fair bit more information on the page,
      including a new direct compile-scope dependency on maven-project at the
      top of the page, about ten dependencies which were included transitively
      by this new dependency under "Project Transitive Dependencies", and a
      much larger dependency graph just below that, indicating how the
      transitive dependencies are related to our direct dependency set. At the
      bottom, you'll find specific information about each dependency,
      including the project's name, description, and website URL (if one was
      provided).</para>

      <para>This information can help users track down potential conflicts
      with their own project dependencies, not to mention giving valuable
      information about which libraries are needed for this project to
      function.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-issue-tracking">
      <title>Issue Tracking</title>

      <para>All software has issues, ranging from functional bugs to tasks and
      ideas for new features. Likewise, all projects should have an issue
      tracker, so community members can file and track those work items they
      feel need to be addressed.</para>

      <para>However, it's not enough to simply have an issue-tracking system;
      your project also needs to publicize its existence, so new community
      members can find it more easily. Obviously, the project website is an
      ideal place for this sort of information - which brings us to the Issue
      Tracking report. Like the name suggests, this report simply publishes
      the information needed to access your project's issue-tracking
      system.</para>

      <para>Returning once again to our hello-world example, we can see that
      this project doesn't publish any information about its issue tracker. We
      can remedy this by adding a small section to the POM, which simply lists
      the issue-tracking system type and its web URL:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Listing a Project's Issue Tracking Settings</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;issueManagement&gt;
    &lt;system&gt;bugzilla&lt;/system&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://dev.example.com/issues/hello-world&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/issueManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>After adding this and regenerating the site, you should see a page
      with two links when you click on the Issue Tracking link under Project
      Information: The first one will link to the Bugzilla project website,
      and the other should point to our own project's issue tracker at
      http://dev.example.com/issues/hello-world. This should give users enough
      information to find the issue-tracking system used by our project, along
      with more information about the system itself (courtesy of that
      application's project website).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-mailing-lists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>

      <para>Mailing lists are one of the most ubiquitous modes of
      collaboration in the open source world. They provide a persistent, open
      communication channel that fosters a high level of participation. They
      also run on infrastructure that is well-understood and well-supported by
      a diverse array of applications, on all platforms. As such, they form
      the backbone of most collaborative development efforts.</para>

      <para>There are five basic elements of information that a user needs to
      know about each of your project's mailing lists (projects often have an
      array of mailing lists, to host separate types of discussion):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the name of the mailing list, to help when referring to
          it</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the email address to use when subscribing to the list</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the email address to use when unsubscribing from the
          list</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the email address to use when posting messages to the
          list</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>at least one list-archive URL, for historical reference</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The first is obvious; having a name for each mailing list makes
      referring to those lists in an unambiguous way simpler. The second and
      third elements (subscribe/unsubscribe addresses) are necessary to
      account for the variability between mailing-list management
      applications, which all handle such requests differently. Next, users
      will obviously need to know the address to which they should send new
      messages bound for the list. And finally, users need the ability to
      search a permanent, historical record of each mailing list. This will
      help them research different aspects of the project's behavior, and
      understand the historical context of discussions that are taking place
      on the list at the present moment.</para>

      <para>So, in order to publish a reference to this critical collaboration
      infrastructure on our hello-world project's website, we need to
      configure the Mailing Lists report. Assuming our project has a somewhat
      minimal set of mailing lists that handle user, development, and
      system-notification traffic, we can add the following section to the POM
      to configure this report:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Listing a Project's Mailing Lists</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;mailingLists&gt;
    &lt;mailingList&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Hello-World Users&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;post&gt;hello-world-users@dev.example.com&lt;/post&gt;
      &lt;subscribe&gt;hello-world-users-subscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/subscribe&gt;
      &lt;unsubscribe&gt;hello-world-users-unsubscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/unsubscribe&gt;
      &lt;archive&gt;http://dev.example.com/mail-archives/hello-world/users&lt;/archive&gt;
      &lt;otherArchives&gt;
        &lt;otherArchive&gt;http://www.nabble.com/Hello---World---Users-f000.html&lt;/otherArchive&gt;
      &lt;/otherArchives&gt;
    &lt;/mailingList&gt;
    &lt;mailingList&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Hello-World Developers&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;post&gt;hello-world-dev@dev.example.com&lt;/post&gt;
      &lt;subscribe&gt;hello-world-dev-subscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/subscribe&gt;
      &lt;unsubscribe&gt;hello-world-dev-unsubscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/unsubscribe&gt;
      &lt;archive&gt;http://dev.example.com/mail-archives/hello-world/developers&lt;/archive&gt;
      &lt;otherArchives&gt;
        &lt;otherArchive&gt;http://www.nabble.com/Hello---World---Dev-f000.html&lt;/otherArchive&gt;
      &lt;/otherArchives&gt;
    &lt;/mailingList&gt;
    &lt;mailingList&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Hello-World Notifications&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;post&gt;hello-world-notifications@dev.example.com&lt;/post&gt;
      &lt;subscribe&gt;hello-world-notifications-subscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/subscribe&gt;
      &lt;unsubscribe&gt;hello-world-notifications-unsubscribe@dev.example.com&lt;/unsubscribe&gt;
    &lt;/mailingList&gt;
  &lt;/mailingLists&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When you regenerate the site and refresh the Mailing Lists report,
      you'll notice that all three of our mailing lists are present and
      accounted for. You may also notice that the notifications list doesn't
      have archives of any sort; this is by design, since notifications are
      trantient by nature. Users hitting this page will now have all the
      information they need to join the community in a very real and vocal
      way.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-project-licenses">
      <title>Project License</title>

      <para>Perhaps one of the most important pieces of information to be
      published about your project is its license. This document specifies
      whether and how others are authorized to make use of your project. In
      the open-source world, the project license can determine whether two
      libraries are able to be used together or not, since some open-source
      licenses are incompatible with one another. In the commercial world, the
      license document has legal ramifications, not only because it specifies
      what users are allowed to do with the project, but also since it defines
      what sort of warranty or guarantees your company is placing on this
      project and its resulting binary.</para>

      <para>Needless to say, no project website can be complete without a
      clear indication of the project's licensing. To that end, we should
      configure the Project License report in our own hello-world project. For
      simplicity, let's assume this is an open-source project. Because we're
      also sympathetic to the business users of the project, let's make use of
      the Apache Public License (version 2.0) to define our terms:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Listing a Project's Software License</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;licenses&gt;
    &lt;license&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;The Apache Software License, Version 2.0&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.txt&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;distribution&gt;repo&lt;/distribution&gt;
    &lt;/license&gt;
  &lt;/licenses&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Most of the elements in the above section have obvious meaning;
      however, the distribution element bears some explanation. This element
      specifies what sort of distribution the stated license allows. The two
      supported types are currently:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>repo - meaning the project binary can be distributed via a
          Maven repository</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>manual - meaning the project binary must be downloaded
          manually and installed before it can be used.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The manual mode is usually indicated for projects that have a
      click-through license agreement on their website, or else simply want to
      maintain strict control over the integrity of the binaries they publish
      (much the way the Eclipse Foundation, with its Eclipse Public License -
      or EPL - does).</para>

      <para>Returning once more to our own project, if you regenerate the site
      and refresh the Project Licenses report, you'll see on prominent display
      the title of the license and its full text. This information will
      provide the user with very clear licensing information for our
      project.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-project-summary">
      <title>Project Summary</title>

      <para>It may seem obvious, but every project should have a very clear
      identity. This not only means having an unambiguous identity, but also
      stating that identity clearly on the project website. An identity may
      take the form of a simple project name, used to locate the project on a
      site like SourceForge or Freshmeat; or, it may explain the exact
      coordinates of that project's binary and other artifacts in a Maven
      repository. Whatever the project's internal culture, it's important to
      provide the simplest route to consumption for users. This means being
      proactive and telling them where to find the project under various
      organizational systems.</para>

      <para>The Project Summary report provides this identity - along with
      other basic information about the project and its organization - to the
      user. Of particular interest here is the Maven repository coordinates
      for the project, which allow users to refer to the project as a
      dependency within their own POMs.</para>

      <para>Our hello-world project already provides some of the information
      necessary to complete this report: we have the artifact identity in the
      Maven repository, along with the project's name and description. By
      adding two small sections to the POM, we can give our users a complete
      picture of who develops this project, and where to find it in the Maven
      repository:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring a Project's Organization</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;url&gt;http://dev.example.com/sites/hello-world&lt;/url&gt;
  
  &lt;organization&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Example Software Foundation&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://www.example.com&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/organization&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Regenerate and refresh once again, and you should now see a
      section containing our organization's name and main website URL, along
      with the URL pointing to the hello-world project's main page.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Usually teams developing standalone applications will want to
        separate the main project website from the one containing these
        project reports, which tend to be most useful to developers and
        integrators. In these cases, the project url above (not to be confused
        with the organization url) should probably point at the main website,
        with this developer-specific site content hosted as a
        subsection.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-project-team">
      <title>Project Team</title>

      <para>The people who work so hard to make your project successful
      deserve recognition; particularly when they take the time to contribute
      improvements from the outside, without commit access to the code. These
      contributors are critical to the health of a project, and they're also
      some of the easiest people to overlook. The project's website should
      make a special effort to recognize those who keep the lights on, and
      keep things humming along.</para>

      <para>Aside from giving credit, providing a list of developers on the
      project website has its practical benefits. With a developer list, users
      can identify the people in the community who are most likely to have the
      answers to tough questions, and organizations know who to ask for tips
      on finding commercial support the project. Perhaps more importantly,
      these are the people you should turn to if you want to get involved in
      the project, and need some guidance.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, Maven's Project Team report can fill this need. Let's
      flesh out this report for the hello-world project, using some imaginary
      developers/contributors. Configuring this report is a simple process of
      adding two new sections to the POM, like this:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>List Contributors and Developers</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;developers&gt;
    &lt;developer&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;jsmith&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Joan Smith&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;jsmith@example.com&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://blogs.example.com/jsmith&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;organization&gt;ESF&lt;/organization&gt;
      &lt;organizationUrl&gt;http://www.example.com&lt;/organizationUrl&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;Architect&lt;/role&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;Developer&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;-5&lt;/timezone&gt;
      &lt;properties&gt;
        &lt;gpg-key&gt;jsmith@personal.com&lt;/gpg-key&gt;
      &lt;/properties&gt;
    &lt;/developer&gt;
    &lt;developer&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;pbunyan&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Paul Bunyan&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;pbunyan@elsewhere.com&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://www.blogs.com/paul&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;organization&gt;Elsewhere, Inc.&lt;/organization&gt;
      &lt;organizationUrl&gt;http://www.elsewhere.com&lt;/organizationUrl&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;Developer&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;-8&lt;/timezone&gt;
      &lt;properties&gt;
        &lt;gpg-key&gt;pbunyan@elsewhere.com&lt;/gpg-key&gt;
      &lt;/properties&gt;
    &lt;/developer&gt;
  &lt;/developers&gt;
  
  &lt;contributors&gt;
    &lt;contributor&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;George W. Newman&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;gwnewman@example.com&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;Mascot&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;-5&lt;/timezone&gt;
    &lt;/contributor&gt;
    &lt;contributor&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Andrea Penn&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;email&gt;apenn@writers.org&lt;/email&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://www.blogs.com/apenn&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;organization&gt;Writers Foundation&lt;/organization&gt;
      &lt;organizationUrl&gt;http://www.writers.org&lt;/organizationUrl&gt;
      &lt;roles&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;Documentation&lt;/role&gt;
      &lt;/roles&gt;
      &lt;timezone&gt;0&lt;/timezone&gt;
    &lt;/contributor&gt;
  &lt;/contributors&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When you refresh, you should see that the community members who
      are active in our project are listed in one of two sections in the
      Project Team report, along with any identity or contact information they
      have supplied. From looking at this page, it should be fairly clear who
      you might want to ask about the design of our project (Ms. Smith), or
      about a typo you found in the documentation (Ms. Penn, though she can't
      actually commit the corrections).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-source-repository">
      <title>Source Repository</title>

      <para>The final step in laying a good foundation for a project website
      is particularly critical for open-source projects. If your project is
      developed under an open-source license, you absolutely have to give
      people access to your source code. This enables outsiders to review your
      code, and suggest improvement. It also gives them an opportunity to use
      the project's source code to aid in debugging. If your project is
      commercial or operates under some other brand of closed-source
      licensing, it's still a good idea to provide information for accessing
      the project sources; in the closed-source case, it just becomes a
      question of where you publish this project website (which is, almost by
      definition, a developer-oriented site). Maven's Source Repository report
      gives you the ability to provide this sort of documentation.</para>

      <para>Since we've chosen an open-source license for our example
      hello-world project, it is imperative that we document the location of
      our project's source repository. Like all the other reports we've
      covered here, this just involves a small addition to the POM:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Adding a Project's Source Repository</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;scm&gt;
    &lt;developerConnection&gt;scm:svn:https://dev.example.com/svn/repo/hello-world/trunk&lt;/developerConnection&gt;
    &lt;connection&gt;scm:svn:http://dev.example.com/scm/hello-world/trunk&lt;/connection&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://dev.example.com/svn/viewvc/hello-world/trunk&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/scm&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When you refresh this report, you should see three important
      pieces of information:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The type of source-control system in use, including a link to
          instructions for using that system, if available.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A link to the web-enabled view on our project's SCM system
          (linked to the URL given in the url element above).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Instructions for retrieving a local copy of our project's
          source code, using the appropriate source-control client (such as
          svn for Subversion). These instructions will include details on
          accessing the source as both a developer with commit rights, and as
          a user with read-only access. Additionally, they may provide
          techniques you should use if you're behind a firewall, or using a
          web proxy.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <note>
        <para>The formatting of URLs within the scm section of the POM is not
        the same throughout. The developerConnection and connection elements
        actually have URLs with multiple nested protocols, such as
        scm:svn:https, while the url element is meant to be a simple http or
        https URL. The extra protocol information is used by Maven's Source
        Control APIs to determine what type of system our project uses. In the
        case of this report, it also tells Maven what type of instructions to
        generate in order to guide the user to the project source code
        effectively. For more information on the URL format for source
        repositories, see the URL Format page on the Maven website, at <ulink
        url="http://maven.apache.org/scm/scm-url-format.html">http://maven.apache.org/scm/scm-url-format.html</ulink>
        page. For more information on which SCM systems are supported by
        Maven, see the Supported SCMs page, at <ulink
        url="http://maven.apache.org/scm/scms-overview.html">http://maven.apache.org/scm/scms-overview.html</ulink>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>With this report configured, we've given our community a great
      touchstone for reference information on the hello-world project. These
      reports will enable easy participation in the hello-world community, and
      should give users the tools they need to get involved in the project
      more deeply. The next step is to publish the documentation specific to
      our project, which may include installation and usage instructions,
      design and architectural documentation, or even screenshots and other
      introductory material.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-additional-reports">
      <title>Configuring Additional Reports</title>

      <para>Looking back at the website we've created so far, it's still
      lacking some important features. Modern project websites - particularly
      those provided by open-source projects - absolutely must provide some
      statistics about the project's source code. For example, an open-source
      project won't get much attention without a decent test suite; to
      reassure prospective users, wouldn't it be a good idea to publish the
      test-result and coverage statistics? Also, when we're talking about Java
      projects, how many successful open-source projects don't publish their
      JavaDoc API documentation to their website?</para>

      <para>We now know from experience that the project-info reports don't
      provide any of this information. How, then, do we supply this
      information to the user? As I mentioned above, Maven provides a rich set
      of project reports that can help you publish everything from basic
      project information -- which we've pretty well covered in the preceding
      section -- to API documentation, test statistics, static code analysis,
      and much more. Since the project-info reports only provide a small
      fraction of this capability, we must configure some additional reports.
      But before we do, it would be best to cover the basics of configuring
      these reports.</para>

      <para>Generally speaking, report configuration in Maven is done in a
      very similar way to plugin configuration. Instead of the build/plugins
      section of the POM, report configuration happens in the
      reporting/plugins section. This section uses nearly the same plugin
      syntax as the build/plugins section, except for two important
      differences:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Report plugins specified here do not need to be explicitly
          bound to a report-set; if no report-set is specified, Maven will
          iterate through all of the mojos defined in each plugin, and add
          bindings for those that implement
          org.apache.maven.reporting.MavenReport.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Instead of execution entries in an executions subsection, the
          reporting section uses report-sets and report-set to separate
          invocations and associated configuration from one another.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>One other thing to take note of is that additional project reports
      (i.e. non-project-info reports) will appear under a new menu called
      Project Reports in the generated website by default.</para>

      <para>Now that we have a basic idea of how to configure project reports
      in the POM, let's explore some of the reports that are available.</para>

      <note>
        <para>A Quick Note on Additional Reports in the Project Website. When
        configuring the reports of the maven-project-info-reports-plugin, we
        noticed that each new report showed up in the Project Information menu
        of our generated website. In this way, the project-info reports are
        unique; all other reports appear under the Project Reports menu by
        default. So, as we talk about the additional reports you can configure
        for your projects, be sure to note the change and look for updates in
        the right spot. And don't worry; I'll remind you!</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-other-reports">
      <title>Other Reports Available from the Maven Project (at ASF)</title>

      <para>Aside from the maven-project-info-reports-plugin, the Apache Maven
      project maintains several additional reports that can provide
      considerable value to a project's website. Each of these reports shares
      some common naming elements with the project-info-reports plugin, namely
      the following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>GroupId: org.apache.maven.plugins</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ArtifactId: maven-something-plugin</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Let's take a look at some of the things that these reports can
      provide for your website.</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-surefire-report">
        <title>maven-surefire-report-plugin</title>

        <para>Your project has unit tests, right? Nevermind, I don't want to
        know...</para>

        <para>If you are running unit tests as part of your build, wouldn't it
        be nice to publish those results to the project website, to keep all
        of your fellow developers (and users) in the loop? Using the Surefire
        report, visitors to your website can see how many tests are
        succeeding, and how fast they're running.</para>

        <note>
          <para>For those of you who missed it, Surefire is the name of
          Maven's unit-testing framework, used to execute tests written with
          JUnit, TestNG, and other testing APIs. Correspondingly, the
          surefire-report plugin contains the report that formats unit test
          results for the project website.</para>
        </note>

        <para>To illustrate the usage of the Surefire report, let's put our
        hello-world project's test results on its website. To add the Surefire
        report, we add the plugin's identity to the reporting section of the
        POM, like this:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring the Surefire Report</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-surefire-report-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>When you regenerate the website, you should see the Maven
        Surefire Report link appear under the Project Reports menu. If you
        click on this link, you will see a page that with unit-test statistics
        that allow you to see results by summary, package, and individual
        class.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="reporting-sect-javadoc-plugin">
        <title>maven-javadoc-plugin</title>

        <para>Besides unit tests, all projects should have some form of
        documentation within the code itself. In Java, this usually takes the
        form of JavaDocs, which has the nice side effect of allowing that
        documentation to be extracted and published to a website. But, I'm not
        telling you anything new; you've been publishing your JavaDocs for
        years, right?</para>

        <para>To publish the JavaDocs for our hello-world project, we can
        start by adding a reference to the javadoc plugin to our POM's
        reporting section, as follows:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Confguring the Javadoc Report</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-javadoc-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <note>
          <para>Currently, this report does not work with the site:run mojo.
          To view the output of this report, use the file-based previewing
          strategy discussed at the beginning of this chapter. The file you're
          looking for is target/site/apidocs/index.html in your hello-world
          project directory.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Since our source code uses classes from external libraries
        (admittedly, only java.lang.String so far in this example), we should
        provide links to any external JavaDocs that we need. Configuring these
        links is simple:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Customizing the Javadoc Report</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-javadoc-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;links&gt;
            &lt;link&gt;http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api&lt;/link&gt;
          &lt;/links&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
        
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>This time, when we regenerate the site, we should see that the
        java.lang.String reference in App.java is hyperlinked to the Sun JDK
        JavaDocs.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="reporting-sect-changelog-plugin">
        <title>maven-changelog-plugin</title>

        <para>The changelog plugin reads your project's SCM, and produces
        three different types of reports from the information it finds
        there:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The changelog report renders a page called Change Log which
            lists the SCM commits that have taken place in the recent past,
            providing the developer, a list of files changed, and the commit
            message for each.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dev-activity report renders a page called Developer
            Activity which provides summary statistics, organized by
            developer, which include the number of commits and number of files
            changed on your project in the recent past. Results are listed in
            alphabetical order.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The file-activity report is similar to the dev-activity
            report, except it organizes its statistics by file name. It
            produces a page called File Activity with statistics that show how
            many times each file was changed in the recent past. Results are
            listed in descending order, according to the number of
            changes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To enable these reports, you have to have a few basic pieces of
        information in your project's POM. The most important -- for obvious
        reasons -- is the scm section. This gives the changelog reports the
        connection information it needs to retrieve the SCM logs. If you want
        to use the dev-activity report, you'll also need to provide a
        developers section, since the report pulls the list of available
        developer names from that section. If a developer is not in the
        developers list, her recent contributions will not show up on the
        dev-activity report. For more information on configuring these
        sections of the POM, see the Project Team and Source Repository
        configuration summaries, in the project-info section above.</para>

        <para>Once you've configured those two sections, you'll also have to
        add the maven-changelog-plugin to your reporting section, like
        this:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring the Maven Changelog Report</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-changelog-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>Regenerate and refresh, and you'll see these new reports pop up
        under the Project Reports menu. If you've configured your scm and
        developers sections correctly, you should notice that the dev-activity
        report links to the Project Team report from the project-info plugin.
        Likewise, each file mentioned in these three reports is linked back to
        the SCM system, so you can browse its contents.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="reporting-sect-sample-configuration">
        <title>Sample Configuration</title>

        <para>If you don't have a project in SCM to play with yet, you can try
        modifying your hello-world project with the following information, to
        see a sample report:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring the SCM Information for Changelog</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;developers&gt;
    &lt;developer&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;jdcasey&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;John&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;/developer&gt;
    &lt;developer&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;jvanzyl&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;Jason&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;/developer&gt;
  &lt;/developers&gt;

  ...

  &lt;scm&gt;
    &lt;developerConnection&gt;scm:svn:https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/maven/components/trunk&lt;/developerConnection&gt;
    &lt;connection&gt;scm:svn:http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/maven/components/trunk&lt;/connection&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/maven/components/trunk&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/scm&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-customizing-file-links">
      <title>Customizing Your File Links</title>

      <para>Sometimes, you may wish to have the file links in these reports
      point to a web-based SCM tool, like ViewVC or Fisheye. To enable this,
      the changelog plugin provides the following configuration point (the
      example uses the ViewVC system at svn.apache.org, for use with the tip
      above):</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Customizing File Links in the Changelog Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-changelog-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;displayFileDetailUrl&gt;http://svn.apache.org/viewvc%FILE%?view=markup&lt;/displayFileDetailUrl&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Unfortunately, when you make this customization, the changelog
      report no longer provides links to the specific revisions in each entry,
      only the latest revision.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-core-reporting-plugins"> 
    <title>Core Reporting Plugins</title>

    <section id="reporting-sect-changes-plugin">
      <title>maven-changes-plugin</title>

      <para>In contrast to the maven-changelog-plugin, the changes plugin
      extracts a list of changes in the project from either its issue-tracking
      system or an XML-formatted changelog file maintained in the project's
      directory structure. They may seem redundant at first blush, but these
      two reports are actually complementary, each filling in a little more
      information about the project's current release or snapshot (depending
      on what the published website is based on).</para>

      <para>This plugin offers two different reports, depending on what method
      you employ to track the issues you've resolved. If your project uses
      JIRA from Atlassian, the changes plugin will include the jira-report,
      which links to the Jira Report page. If you use a changes.xml file
      (which could be maintained manually or generated from some other
      issue-tracking system), then it will include the changes-report, which
      links to the Changes Report page.</para>

      <para>If your project uses JIRA, the changes-report is probably not of
      interest to you. Instead, you can simply verify that the information in
      your POM's issueManagement section resembles this:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the Maven Changes Plugin</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;issueManagement&gt;
    &lt;system&gt;jira&lt;/system&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/MNG&lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/issueManagement&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Regenerate and refresh, and you'll see the Jira Report link appear
      under the Project Reports menu. By default, this report will contain the
      top 100 issues, sorted in order of creation date and priority -
      regardless of whether they're open or closed.</para>

      <para>If your project doesn't use JIRA, you will have to get by with
      some level of manual maintenance of the changes report. In some cases,
      this may mean maintaining the file (found under src/changes/changes.xml
      by default) and keeping in SCM along with other project files. Below is
      a sample changes.xml:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Maintaining Changes Manually in changes.xml</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;document&gt;
  &lt;properties&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hello-World Issues&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author email="pbunyan@elsewhere.com"&gt;Paul Bunyan&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;/properties&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;release version="1.1" date="2007-03-01" description="Version 1.1 Release Notes"&gt;
      &lt;action dev="pbunyan" type="add"&gt;
        Added changes.xml
      &lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action dev="jsmith" type="fix" issue="01011"&gt;
        Fix the Widget Control Panel.
      &lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action dev="jsmith" type="remove" due-to="Aaron Penn" due-to-email="apenn@writers.org"&gt;
        Fixed typos in How-To document.
      &lt;/action&gt;
    &lt;/release&gt;

    &lt;release version="1.0" date="2007-01-01" description="Version 1.0 Release"&gt;
      &lt;action dev="pbunyan" type="update"&gt;
        Uploaded documentation.
      &lt;/action&gt;
    &lt;/release&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/document&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>If you include this sample report under src/changes/changes.xml,
      then regenerate and refresh, you should see the Changes Report link
      appear under the Project Reports menu. The resulting report will list
      each issue in the changes document, in the order it appears. action
      sections with the issue attribute will have that issue number linked to
      the issue-tracking system (if you've configured the issueManagement
      section). The due-to and due-to-email attributes of the action element
      will be rendered as "Thanks to $due-to", with the due-to name rendered
      as a link to the email given by $due-to-email. Finally, the dev
      attribute of the action element is linked back to the appropriate team
      member entry in the Project Team report, if it has been configured
      correctly.</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-limit-jira-closed"> 
        <title>Limit the Jira Report to Closed Items</title>

        <para>If you'd like to limit the Jira Report to only display closed
        issues (which will approximate a release notes-style of report),
        simply include the following configuration for the changes
        plugin:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring JIRA Report to List Closed Items</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-changes-report&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;statusIds&gt;Closed&lt;/statusIds&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>When you regenerate and refresh, you should notice that none of
        the items in the Jira Report have a status other than Closed.</para>

        <note>
          <para>The statusIds configuration accepts a comma-separated list of
          statuses, so you can tailor the exact set of issue-status types to
          include in the report.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-checkstyle-plugin"> 
      <title>maven-checkstyle-plugin</title>

      <para>The Checkstyle plugin performs static code analysis, and generates
      a report of how well it adheres with predetermined code-style policies
      -- using <ulink
      url="http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net">Checkstyle</ulink>, of course.
      The single report that this plugin provides -- checkstyle -- links to
      Checkstyle in the Project Reports menu, and provides summary statistics
      about which rules were violated, how many times, and by which file(s).
      At the bottom of the report, it gives the line number for each rule
      violation. By default, it uses the Sun code-style guidelines.</para>

      <para>Many teams use some form of modified code style, other than that
      suggested by Sun. Therefore, it's important to that we can specify our
      own policy file used to evaluate the project's source code. To
      accommodate common cases, the plugin has four built-in policy
      files:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>config/sun_checks.xml applies the Sun code-style
          guidelines.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>config/turbine_checks.xml applies those from the Turbine
          project.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>config/avalon_checks.xml applies the Avalon code style.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>config/maven_checks.xml applies the style used by Maven
          projects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Beyond these built-ins, it's also possible to specify your own
      custom rules, using the configLocation parameter. All policy files
      should conform to the Checkstyle Checker module XML format
      ({{http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net/config.html#Modules}}). To specify
      your own file, add a configuration similar to the following:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the Maven Checkstyle Plugin</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-checkstyle-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;configLocation&gt;src/checkstyle/checkstyle-configuration.xml&lt;/configLocation&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>The checkstyle plugin uses three strategies to resolve the value
        of the configLocation. They are, in order: classpath-resource, URL,
        and file. That is, Checkstyle will look for a resource in your
        classpath with a patch matching the configLocation. If it cannot find
        one, it will attempt to construct a new java.net.URL instance from the
        configLocation, open a stream, and download the configuration. Failing
        that, it will try to find a file that matches the given path, and load
        it from there.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The checkstyle plugin offers all the same options that would be
      available if you were to run Checkstyle directly, with the addition of
      some nice features for referencing configurations outside of your local
      project directory. Here are some examples of useful features provided by
      the checkstyle plugin:</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-review-checkstyle">
        <title>Reviewing Your Checkstyle Configuration File</title>

        <para>When the configLocation is successfully resolved, it's contents
        will be copied to the
        $\{project.build.directory\}/checkstyle-checker.xml file (usually,
        $\{project.build.directory\} == $\{basedir\}/target). This gives you
        the opportunity to review the actual policies against which the source
        code has been evaluated, which can be handy when the configuration
        comes from a URL or a resource embedded in a dependency jar.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="reporting-sect-view-license-header"> 
        <title>Verify Your Source Code License Header</title>

        <para>One very useful feature of Checkstyle is that it allows you to
        verify that each source file has the correct license header. License
        headers are usually block comments (or blocks of single-line comments)
        that appear at the top of each source file, to give a clear indication
        of the license terms applied to that file. They are very common among
        open-source projects (usually, they're mandatory) but they could also
        be quite useful in proprietary code.</para>

        <para>To verify that all of your project's source files have the
        appropriate license header, paste that header into its own file. For
        the purposes of this example, we'll copy the following into
        src/checkstyle/checkstyle-header.txt:</para>

        <screen>^package 
^\s*$
^/\*\s*$
^ \*\s* Copyright 2007, Example Software Foundation$
^\s*$
^ \*\s+ This is the project license. See http://dev.example.com/LICENSE.txt for more information.$
^ \*/\s*$
^\s*$
</screen>

        <para>You'll notice that the header used by Maven consists of a series
        of regular expressions. This is the format used by the RegexpHeader
        module; it gives us the flexibility to adapt to minor whitespace
        deviations introduced by code formatters and other tools, without
        sacrificing the content of the license header.</para>

        <para>Next, we must configure the configLocation parameter to refer to
        the Maven code rules. To accommodate for a hard-coded license header
        that made it out in the latest release of the checkstyle plugin, we
        can't use the config/maven_checks.xml built-in rules. Instead, we can
        reference the updated configuration in SVN as follows. For
        convenience, we're also going to tell the checkstyle plugin which
        header file to use for the license check:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring Checkstyle License Header Check</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;configuration&gt;
  &lt;configLocation&gt;http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/maven/plugins/trunk/maven-checkstyle-plugin/src/main/resources/config/maven_checks.xml&lt;/configLocation&gt;
  &lt;headerLocation&gt;src/checkstyle/checkstyle-header.txt&lt;/headerLocation&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>If we regenerate and refresh, then click on the Checkstyle link
        under Project Reports, we should see that the App.java file has a
        non-compliant license header. We can fix that by adding the following
        comment to src/main/java/book/reporting/App.java:</para>

        <screen>package book.reporting;

/*
 * This is the project license. See LICENSE.txt for more information.
 */
...
</screen>

        <para>This time when we regenerate, we'll see that the previous
        Checkstyle error has gone away.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-jxr-plugin"> 
      <title>maven-jxr-plugin</title>

      <para>JXR is a source-code cross-referencing API maintained by the Maven
      project. The JXR plugin renders your project's source code to XHTML,
      with links for each line number to allow direct referencing of your
      source code, and links from source file to source file, wherever a
      cross-reference exists. In addition, if you've configured your POM to
      include JavaDoc API documentation, each browsable source file rendered
      by JXR will contain a link the corresponding JavaDoc page.</para>

      <para>When you add the JXR plugin to your POM, it will create up to two
      new links under the Project Reports menu. One, called Source Xref,
      contains the cross-referenced pages for your main project sources. This
      link will always be included by JXR. The other link is called Test
      Source Xref, and contains a similar set of cross-reference pages for the
      unit-test source code for your project. Whether the Test Source Xref
      pages are produced or not is up to you; they are provided by default,
      but you can exclude them by disabling a single boolean parameter in the
      plugin's configuration.</para>

      <para>As you might guess, the JXR plugin is extremely simple to use; to
      illustrate just how easy, let's try an example with the hello-world
      project. Begin by adding the JXR plugin to the reporting section, like
      this:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the JXR Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-jxr-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>Like the javadoc plugin, the jxr plugin is not compatible with
        the current version of the site:run mojo. Therefore, to preview these
        reports, you'll have to use the alternate command discussed at the
        beginning of the chapter:</para>
      </note>

      <screen>hello-world$ mvn clean site
</screen>

      <para>Then, load the rendered website from the target/site directory
      structure within your hello-world project directory.</para>

      <para>When you regenerate and preview this time, you should see both the
      Source Xref and Test Source Xref links under the Project Reports menu.
      If you look at these new reports, you'll quickly notice that the sample
      code -- one class and one test case -- are far too simplistic to show
      any sort of cross-referencing. You should notice that each line in the
      reference page has a unique anchor, allowing you to reference any line
      directly from an external page. Also, the link to the corresponding
      JavaDoc page at the top of the the App reference page (JavaDocs are not
      normally produced for unit tests, so you may not see a corresponding
      link in the AppTest page).</para>

      <para>But let's turn our attention back to the cross-referencing
      feature. We can make two relatively easy changes to make cross-reference
      links show up. To create a cross-reference in the main project source,
      let's create a second class called Configuration for our application,
      and allow each App instance to accept a Configuration instance via a
      setConfiguration method. First, the new class:</para>

      <screen>package book.reporting;

public class Configuration
{
    ...
}
</screen>

      <para>Now, the change to the App class:</para>

      <screen>...

public class App
{
    ...
    private Configuration configuration;
    
    public void setConfiguration( Configuration configuration )
    {
        this.configuration = configuration;
    }
}
</screen>

      <para>This time, when we regenerate (remember, you cannot use the
      site:run mojo!) and preview, you'll notice that the cross-reference
      pages are a little more interesting. Specifically, the source listing
      for the App class now contains a link to the Configuration class.
      Alright, it's not a lot more interesting, but this is just a simple
      example!</para>

      <warning>
        <para>One thing the JXR plugin will not currently handle is
        cross-references that exist between unit-test code and main-project
        code. While this is clearly an oversight in this plugin's
        implementation, browsing from test code to main code is not generally
        considered the strongest use case for this plugin. Far more useful is
        the ability to browse and link to a project's source code, without
        getting into the arcane paths and strange interfaces of many SCM web
        front-ends.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-clover-plugin">
      <title>maven-clover-plugin</title>

      <para><ulink url="http://www.cenqua.com/clover">Clover</ulink> is a tool
      from <ulink url="http://www.cenqua.com">Cenqua</ulink> which analyzes
      code coverage. For those who somehow don't know, code coverage is a form
      of analysis that measures how much of your project's source code is
      actually tested by a suite of tests. In most cases, code coverage refers
      to a measurement of how well your unit tests exercise the main-project
      source code. For each line in each of your main-project source files,
      Clover will give you a number that corresponds to how many separate unit
      tests traversed that line of code. While traversal of a particular line
      doesn't necessarily mean that code is adequately tested, it's quite
      obvious what a count of zero means.</para>

      <para>Maven's Clover plugin binds the Clover tool into your build
      process, and allows it to do one of several things. First, it can fail a
      conventional build (that is, one aimed at producing a project binary by
      compiling, archiving, etc.) if the average code-coverage percentage is
      too low. This has obvious quality-control attraction. However, this
      chapter is really more concerned with the second possible action:
      reporting those code-coverage statistics to the world, through the
      Clover report (under the Project Reports menu...I'm sure you see a
      pattern here) that this plugin can generate.</para>

      <para>Before you can get started with the Clover plugin, you should know
      that Clover is not free software; you must obtain a valid license file
      if you want to generate this report. The good news is that Cenqua offers
      free, 30-day trial licenses on their website (again, that's
      {{http://www.cenqua.com}}). Once you've downloaded your evaluation
      license, we can proceed with an example.</para>

      <para>First of all, the clover report requires a Clover database for the
      project, which can be generated with the instrument mojo. The instrument
      mojo is not a report, so it has to be configured in the build section of
      the POM:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring Clover to Instrument Byte Code</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;build&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-clover-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;licenseLocation&gt;clover.license&lt;/licenseLocation&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
        
        &lt;executions&gt;
          &lt;execution&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;mk-clover-db&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;phase&gt;pre-site&lt;/phase&gt;
            &lt;goals&gt;
              &lt;goal&gt;instrument&lt;/goal&gt;
            &lt;/goals&gt;
          &lt;/execution&gt;
        &lt;/executions&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/build&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>We bind the instrument mojo to the pre-site lifecycle phase,
        which is present in the site lifecycle (the one that gets executed
        whenever you issue the command mvn site). This allows Clover to run
        automatically as part of the site build. Also, remember that you had
        to download that evaluation license; its location is configured above
        for Clover to use. This single configuration will make the license
        file available to both the instrument and clover mojos (reports are
        mojos, too, in the strictest sense).</para>
      </note>

      <para>Next, since we want to include the Clover report in our project's
      website, we must also include an entry in the reporting section for
      Clover:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Confguring the Clover Plugin</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-clover-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>Again, just like the JavaDoc plugin, the clover report is not
        compatible with the site:run mojo. To preview this report, use the
        alternate method discussed at the beginning of the chapter. This
        involves issuing the following command:</para>
      </note>

      <screen>hello-world$ mvn clean site
</screen>

      <para>Then, load the generated website from the target/site directory
      structure within your hello-world project directory.</para>

      <para>When you regenerate and preview, you should see the Clover report
      link present under Project Reports. When you click on the Clover report,
      you'll notice that the App class has 50% code coverage (owing to the
      methods we added in this and the AppTest test case in the
      maven-jxr-plugin section above). Again, the important thing to take away
      from this report is not the idea that the setApplicationName method is
      adequately tested; rather, the value of this coverage report is to show
      that the setConfiguration method is not tested.</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-generate-pdf-clover">
        <title>Generate PDF and XML Output from Your Clover Results</title>

        <para>A nice, XHTML code-coverage report that's embedded directly in
        the project website is really convenient for many users. However,
        there are times when you may want to include PDF or even XML versions
        of the same report. PDFs are nice because they can be downloaded for
        offline perusal, and XML is great as a source for further machine
        processing of the data produced by Clover.</para>

        <para>To render our Clover report in PDF, XML, and XHTML
        simulatneously, all we have to do is add a small configuration snippet
        to the clover plugin:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuing the Clover Report to Generate PDF and
            XML</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-clover-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuation&gt;
          &lt;generateXml&gt;true&lt;/generateXml&gt;
          &lt;generatePdf&gt;true&lt;/generatePdf&gt;
          &lt;!-- generateHtml is an option, but it's already true by default. --&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <para>Now, regenerate and refresh. Since we're working off the
        filesystem for previewing purposes, it's possible to go to the
        target/site/clover directory without having a webserver redirect you
        to target/site/clover/index.html. You can take advantage of this fact
        to view the regenerated clover output directory. Since we've enabled
        PDF and XML output, in addition to XHTML, we can now see two new files
        in the target/site/clover directory: clover.pdf and clover.xml. To
        expose these alternative report formats to users, simply provide links
        in your website content or navigation menu.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-pmd-plugin">
      <title>maven-pmd-plugin</title>

      <para>Similar to Checkstyle (discussed above), <ulink
      url="http://pmd.sourceforge.net">PMD</ulink> is another tool that
      performs static analysis on your source code. However, where Checkstyle
      looks for violations in the accepted code-style guidelines, PMD is more
      concerned with finding potential problems in the code that could
      eventually express themselves as bugs in the running product. In
      addition, the PMD plugin also provides a cut-and-paste detector (CPD) to
      detect duplicate code that could cause inconsistencies in your project
      (as one copy is modified but the other is not).</para>

      <para>By default, the PMD plugin generates two reports, called PMD
      Report and CPD Report, under the Project Reports menu. To include these
      reports, simply add the following to your reporting section:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the PMD Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-pmd-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>After inserting the above lines into the hello-world project POM,
      regenerate and refresh the project website (note that site:run works
      fine here). If you click on the PMD Report link, you'll see that we
      already have one violation (from the code we wrote for the JXR plugin,
      above). Basically, PMD is saying that it's bad practice to assign and
      store an instance variable that is never used. If you didn't follow the
      example given in the JXR plugin section above, then you probably won't
      see any errors at all.</para>

      <para>To force the issue, and make sure we have some content for this
      report, let's modify the App code to contain a couple of violations of
      basic PMD rules:</para>

      <screen>...

public class App
{
    private String applicationName;
    
    public String getApplicationName()
    {
        if ( applicationName == null )
        {
            // empty if statement, to trigger a PMD reporting flag!
        }
        
        return applicationName;
    }
    
    public void setApplicationName( String applicationName )
        throws Exception
    {
        this.applicationName = applicationName;
    }
    ...
}
</screen>

      <para>The Basic PMD rule-set doesn't allow empty if statements. Sure
      enough, when we regenerate the website and refresh the PMD Report, we
      can see a new error message, indicating that the code we just added
      contains an empty if statement. It's also important to notice that if
      you still have the JXR report in the POM from the examples earlier, the
      PMD plugin will notice this and link each problem listing directly to
      the corresponding line in the source reference. Remember, though, that
      the JXR report doesn't work with the site:run goal, so you'll have to
      use the filesystem-style preview to actually follow these links.</para>

      <para>Before we dig into the PMD Report any further, let's turn our
      attention to the CPD Report. As I mentioned earlier, this page lists
      cases of possible cut-and-paste programming; areas where the code is the
      same, but where modification of one (and not the other) could create
      inconsistent behavior in the running binary. Cut-and-paste practices
      cause a enough of a maintenance headache that it pays to take steps
      early to try to minimize the endless (and, in some cases, mindless)
      duplication they embody.</para>

      <para>If you click on the CPD Report generated against the hello-world
      code, you'll see that there are no detected cut-and-paste problems. To
      make things interesting, let's re-create the App class
      (src/main/java/book/reporting/App.java) under a different package --
      say, book/reporting/services. As the report implies, you can trigger an
      error by simply copying the App.java file to the
      src/main/java/book/reporting/services directory (though for correctness,
      I also change the package in the new file):</para>

      <screen>package book.reporting.services;
...
public class App 
{
    ...
}
</screen>

      <para>Now, we have to make one more important modification to the POM.
      Since the CPD report's default configuration is to let any duplications
      under 100 lines in length slip through, we need to dial this down so our
      little example shows up:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Customizing Behavior of the PMD Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-pmd-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;!-- CPD configuration, for small examples. --&gt;
          &lt;minimumTokens&gt;10&lt;/minimumTokens&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Regenerate the website and refresh again, and this time you should
      see the full text of the duplicated code for the two App classes, along
      with JXR links for each (remember, though: JXR doesn't work with
      site:run).</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-pmd-rule-sets">
        <title>Customizing Your PMD Rule-Sets</title>

        <para>By default, the PMD Report checks your source code the Basic,
        Imports, and Unused Code rule-sets. However, at times you may want to
        change this; you may want to use a different mix of built-in
        rule-sets, or maybe you want to include a custom rule-set that you
        created. The PMD plugin supports this, of course, through the rulesets
        configuration parameter. To illustrate, let's take advantage of a new
        problem we introduced earlier in our discussion of this plugin:</para>

        <screen>public void setApplicationName( String applicationName )
    throws Exception
</screen>

        <para>Remember that one? If you winced at the sight of that throws
        Exception clause, you were right to do so. Any lower-level exceptions
        -- even derivatives of RuntimeException, which are normally unchecked
        -- will be channeled through this clause. Even worse, anyone calling
        this method will have to catch java.lang.Exception, then try to make
        sense of the myriad errors it could indicate. PMD has a rule to guard
        against this sort of coding mistake, so let's enable it:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title>Configuring Custom Rule-sets for the PMD Report</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-pmd-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          ...
          &lt;!-- we've already customized this plugin a little for CPD --&gt;
          
          &lt;rulesets&gt;
            &lt;!-- include all of the default rule-sets: --&gt;
            &lt;ruleset&gt;/rulesets/basic.xml&lt;/ruleset&gt;
            &lt;ruleset&gt;/rulesets/imports.xml&lt;/ruleset&gt;
            &lt;ruleset&gt;/rulesets/unusedcode.xml&lt;/ruleset&gt;
            
            &lt;!-- add the rule-set for exception-handling practices --&gt;
            &lt;ruleset&gt;/rulesets/strictexception.xml&lt;/ruleset&gt;
          &lt;/rulesets&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <note>
          <para>We must respecify the default rule-sets here, since PMD cannot
          assume that we still want those when we specify our own
          rule-sets.</para>
        </note>

        <para>When you regenerate and refresh the PMD Report, you should see a
        new error listed, referring to the throws Exception clause above. It's
        important to know that the PMD plugin can accept classpath resources
        (like those in the configuration above), URLs, or filesystem paths for
        ruleset configurations.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-additional-codehaus">
    <title>Additional Reports Available from the Codehaus Mojo Project</title>

    <para>While the reports provided by the Apache Maven project contains many
    valuable additions to the project website, they don't constitute the full
    complement of what's available. Most notably, since Apache projects cannot
    host code that depends on libraries with licenses that are incompatible
    with the Apache Public License (APL), the reports hosted under the Apache
    Maven umbrella cannot contain reporting or metric-gathering tools that
    have certain licenses (GPL and EPL, to name just a couple). For this
    reason, Maven has a sister project called Mojo, hosted at Codehaus, that
    provides a home for these reports.</para>

    <para>Just like those hosted in the Apache Maven project, each of the
    reports hosted at the Codehaus Mojo project shares some certain naming
    elements, namely the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>GroupId: org.codehaus.mojo</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ArtifactId: something-maven-plugin</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Let's take a look at some of the things that the Mojo reports can
    provide for your website.</para>

    <section id="reporting-sect-clirr-plugin">
      <title>clirr-maven-plugin</title>

      <para><ulink url="http://clirr.sourceforge.net">Clirr</ulink> is a nice
      little utility to check for binary and source compatibility between two
      releases of the same project. This sort of check is critical to help
      ensure backward compatibility between minor-version releases of a
      project. To bind this into the build process, Maven provides two mojos
      in the clirr-maven-plugin: the check mojo is used to cause the build to
      fail when a compatibility violation occurs, and the clirr mojo is a
      report that displays the project's compatibility with previous
      releases.</para>

      <para>Since we're primarily concerned with the project website, the
      clirr report is of particular interest here. It generates a link called
      Clirr under the Project Reports menu (where else?). However, before we
      can investigate how to include this report for our hello-world sample
      project, we need a previous release to check against.</para>

      <para>Creating the example environment for this report turns out to be a
      slightly more involved process. First, we must deploy a version of the
      hello-world project to a dummy remote Maven repository, so we'll have
      something to check against. We can do this by adding a
      distributionManagement section to the POM, pointing at our dummy
      repository, and adjusting the POM version so it does't look like a
      SNAPSHOT:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Project Object Model Before Version Upgrade</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
  ...
  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;dummy&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;file://\${java.io.tmpdir}/book-repository&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Having created our new "release" POM, we can deploy it to the new
      dummy repository:</para>

      <screen>mvn clean deploy
</screen>

      <para>Next, we have to add a new repository entry to the hello-world POM
      that points to this dummy repository, so the Clirr plugin can locate the
      previous "release", and update the version to the next SNAPSHOT (as if
      we were ready to develop on that new version):</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Updating the Project's Version number for Clirr</title>

          <programlisting langauge="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;version&gt;1.1-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
  ...
  &lt;repositories&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;dummy&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;file://\${java.io.tmpdir}/book-repository&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
  &lt;/repositories&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Finally, once all of this is setup, we can generate the clirr
      report by adding a simple entry to the reporting section:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the Clirr Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;clirr-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>The Clirr plugin does not seem to be compatible with the
        site:run mojo, so you'll need to use the filesystem-based approach to
        previewing this report. For more information, see the instructions
        near the beginning of this chapter.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Now, regenerate and refresh the project website, and you should
      see the Clirr report link appear. If you click on it, you'll notice that
      there are no differences between the two versions! (I know, I was
      surprised too.)</para>

      <para>So, we have a working Clirr report; now, let's make it
      interesting. Modify the src/main/java/book/reporting/App.java file as
      follows.</para>

      <para>Change this:</para>

      <screen>
    public String getApplicationName()
    {
        if ( configuration == null )
        {
              // empty if statement, to trigger a PMD reporting flag!
        }

        return applicationName;
    }
    
    public void setApplicationName( String applicationName )
        throws Exception
    {
        this.applicationName = applicationName;
    }
</screen>

      <para>To this:</para>

      <screen>
    public String getName()
    {
        if ( configuration == null )
        {
            // empty if statement, to trigger a PMD reporting flag!
        }
        
        return applicationName;
    }
    
    public void setName( String applicationName )
        throws Exception
    {
        this.applicationName = applicationName;
    }
</screen>

      <para>This time, when you refresh, you should see two errors pop up on
      the report. Just like many of the other reports we've discussed, if you
      use the JXR plugin in concert with this one, each error will be linked
      back to the line of source code that caused it.</para>

      <section id="reporting-sect-show-only-errors">
        <title>Show Only Errors, Not Warnings</title>

        <para>So, you don't care about those pesky compatibility warnings? You
        just want them gone from your beautiful report?? Well, say no more. A
        small tweak to the Clirr report configuration, and you're good to
        go:</para>

        <para><example>
            <title></title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;clirr-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;minSeverity&gt;error&lt;/minSeverity&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
          </example></para>

        <note>
          <para>The minSeverity parameter accepts the values: info, warning,
          and error. The default value is warning.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-maven-plugin">
      <title>cobertura-maven-plugin</title>

      <para>Similar to Clover (discussed above), <ulink
      url="http://cobertura.sourceforge.net">Cobertura</ulink> is a
      code-coverage tool. Unlike Clover, Cobertura is released under an
      open-source license (GPL), so you don't have to worry about evaluation
      licenses or an eventual software purchase in order to use Cobertura.
      Both tools generate statistics on the number of unit (or other) tests
      that trigger any particular line of code in your project's sources;
      however, Cobertura also throws in some metrics analyzing your code's
      complexity.</para>

      <para>Like the Clover plugin, the Maven cobertura-maven-plugin provides
      several mojos. Many of these are concerned with managing the statistics
      database used by Cobertura, and with instrumenting the project's classes
      for statistics-gathering. In addition, the check mojo gives you the
      ability to fail the build if your project's code coverage isn't up to
      snuff. However, the mojo we're really after for this chapter is the lone
      report, called simply cobertura. This report generates a page linked
      under Cobertura Test Coverage in the now-familiar Project Reports menu.
      To add this report to our sample project, simply add the following to
      the hello-world POM:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the Cobetura Plugin</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugins&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;cobertura-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>The Cobertura plugin is incompatible with the site:run mojo, so
        be sure to use the filesystem-based approach to previewing your
        project website (discussed near the beginning of the chapter) when
        working with these examples.</para>
      </note>

      <para>When you regenerate the site, and click on the Cobertura Test
      Coverage link, you'll see a report very similar to the Clover report.
      However, notice the extra column on the right, called Complexity. This
      refers to the McCabe cyclomatic code complexity metric for the package
      or class in question, which measures the number of distinct "paths" that
      can traverse that piece of code (to find more information on cyclomatic
      complexity, see the Resources section at the end of this
      chapter).</para>

      <para>While the check mojo offers many options for fine-tuning the
      criteria that a project must pass before the build can succeed, the
      cobertura report offers relatively few. Simple options for generating
      XML in addition to XHTML, for suppressing informational-level messages,
      and for adjusting the maximum memory for testing runs are among the most
      notable. It is worth mentioning that the instrument mojo (which is used
      by the cobertura report) also supports several options for including or
      excluding certain packages and file-sets. However, for most common use
      cases this report just works -- cleanly and simply -- without much
      intervention or configuration.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-findbugs-plugin">
      <title>findbugs-maven-plugin</title>

      <para>Much like the PMD plugin (described above), the <ulink
      url="http://findbugs.sourceforge.net">FindBugs</ulink> report produces a
      list of potential problem errors in your project's source code using
      static analysis techniques. The FindBugs plugin will create a page
      linked to FindBugs Report under Project Reports. To enable this report
      for out hello-world project, add the plugin to the POM as
      follows:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the FindBugs Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;findbugs-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Regenerate and refresh your project website (site:run is fine
      here), and you'll see the report link appear. When you click on the
      link, you'll see a short list of potential problems that FindBugs
      noticed in our source code. Specifically, you'll notice the empty if
      statement listed as a Bug.</para>

      <para>The FindBugs plugin supports a few configuration options that look
      interesting, specifically effort and threshold. The effort parameter
      allows you to tell FindBugs how much memory and time to spend in pinning
      down more subtle bugs. Valid values for this parameter are Min, Default,
      and Max -- can you guess which one it uses by default? The threshold
      parameter tells FindBugs what priority of messages you want to see in
      the output, and supports the values Low, Medium, High, and Exp
      (experimental). Unfortunately, even the configuration for highest output
      did not reveal our ugly little throws Exception clause.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-javancss-plugin">
      <title>javancss-maven-plugin</title>

      <para>The <ulink
      url="http://www.kclee.de/clemens/java/javancss">JavaNCSS</ulink> plugin
      compiles some simple statistics about your project's source code,
      including non-comment source statements (NCSS), number of methods,
      number of classes, and number of javadocs. At the per-method level, it
      also computes cyclomatic complexity statistics. The idea of this report
      is to give you some insight into the distribution of code throughout the
      project, along with the proportion of code that contains formal
      documentation (JavaDocs), so that you can tell identify any hot-spots
      (those in dire need of documentation of refactoring).</para>

      <para>The report it linked to the Project Reports menu (where else?) as
      JavaNCSS Report, and you can enable it by adding the following to the
      hello-world POM:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Including the JavaNCSS Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;javancss-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>When you regenerate and refresh (site:run is fine here), you'll
      find that this report gives a nice code summary of our (very small)
      hello-world project. If any of the table-column headings are confusing,
      just click on the explanation link at the top of each section.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-jdepend-plugin">
      <title>jdepend-maven-plugin</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://clarkware.com/software/JDepend.html">JDepend</ulink> is a
      tool that produces design-quality metrics for your project. These
      metrics can help isolate potential architectural "smells" in your code,
      such as classes with cyclic dependencies, and give an indication of how
      well the project rates in terms of reusability, extensibility,
      maintainability, and other -abilities. Like the JavaNCSS plugin, the
      JDepend plugin for Maven produces a report that can isolate any
      hot-spots in your code which may need refactoring. This report links to
      the Project Reports menu as simply JDepend, and can be included in your
      project's website with the following snippet:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Including the JDepend Report</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;jdepend-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>If you regenerate and refresh (using site:run works fine here),
      then click on JDepend, you'll see the various metrics for the project,
      collected in an overall summary and by package. Toward the bottom, the
      report will list any package cycles (package 'a' has a class 'A' that
      uses class 'B' in package 'b', which uses another class from package
      'a') that it detects.</para>

      <para>JDepend is a very simple report; in fact, the only configuration
      options have to do with controlling which directories to use for output,
      classes, and your project (it's not entirely clear what this one does,
      but it's probably used for relative-path calculations when the classes
      directory is not specified).</para>

      <para>Some of the metrics and explanations provided on this report can
      be pretty dense, and a little abstract. For a more in-depth explanation
      of how best to use this data, I encourage you to visit the JDepend
      website.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="reporting-sect-taglist-plugin">
      <title>taglist-maven-plugin</title>

      <para>Have you ever stopped to think about all those TODO or FIXME tags
      that are lost in your source code? Those tags are created for a purpose,
      as reminders to fix something later, after the current task at hand is
      completed. Many IDEs provide a view that collects these tasks from the
      source code, to make them easier to track down and fix. The point is,
      these tags represent known shortcomings of the existing source code. As
      such, they should be monitored closely, and available to anyone who
      wants to know the health of the project. If the reports section of a
      project website is all about assessing health, then knowing the
      locations of these known warts is a critical element in that
      section.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, the taglist-maven-plugin provides exactly this sort
      of report for your project website. The taglist plugin is one of the
      gems in the Codehaus Mojo project, fitting well with other reports that
      produce critical quality metrics, such as the Surefire (unit test)
      report and the Cobertura report. The taglist report lists all
      occurrences of a set of tags (think @todo or //TODO) in your project
      source code, and lists them on a single page, with links back to the
      browsable source code rendered by JXR (if you've included JXR, that is).
      When generated, it normally appears as Tag List in the Project Reports
      menu.</para>

      <para>When configuring the taglist report, it's important to remember
      that by default, the report will only track @todo and TODO tags. This
      means it will miss FIXME -- a commonly used marker for critical
      shortcomings in the code -- completely. So, when we add the taglist
      report to the hello-world project, we'll go ahead and configure the tags
      at the same time:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Configuring the Taglist Plugin</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  ...
  &lt;reporting&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      ...
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;taglist-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;tags&gt;
            &lt;!-- Add the definitions for FIXME javadoc and code comments... --&gt;
            &lt;tag&gt;@fixme&lt;/tag&gt;
            &lt;tag&gt;FIXME&lt;/tag&gt;
            &lt;tag&gt;@todo&lt;/tag&gt;
            &lt;tag&gt;TODO&lt;/tag&gt;
          &lt;/tags&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/reporting&gt;
  ...
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <para>Now, regenerate and refresh the project (again, site:run is
      perfectly fine here). When you click on the Tag List report, you should
      see sections for each of the tags, and notice that no tags were
      found.</para>

      <para>Let's see if we can make this report a little more interesting.
      We'll start by adding some comments for future improvement to our App
      class:</para>

      <screen>/**
 * Hello world!
 *
 * @todo Provide JavaDocs for the methods in this class!
 */
public class App 
{
    ...
    // TODO: How can we initialize this when the application starts??
    private String applicationName;
    
    // FIXME: Re-add getApplicationName() for backward compatibility
    public String getName()
    {
        // FIXME: This is a NullPointerException waiting to happen...
        if ( configuration.toString() == null )
        ...
    
    // FIXME: Re-add setApplicationName() for backward compatibility
    public void setName( String applicationName )
        throws Exception
        ...
    }
}
</screen>

      <para>Now, if you simply refresh the report in your browser, you'll see
      that there are several tag occurrences listed, each with a link back to
      the JXR source page. This provides the user with an easy way to browse
      the locations where there are known issues that have yet to be
      resolved.</para>

      <para>The taglist report is deceptively simple, yet powerful. There are
      very few configuration options for this report; it simply scans through
      your source code, picking up on the lines that contain one of the tags
      listed. However, aggregating this sort of information into a single-page
      report on the project website can make it very easy to track down the
      areas of the project where the source code is less mature, and could
      fail.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-killer-report">
    <title>Assembling a Killer Report Suite for Your Project</title>

    <para>As we've mentioned several times in this chapter, certain reports
    provide critical metrics for assessing the health of your project.
    Therefore, by publishing the right kinds of reports, your project's
    website can become an indispensible tool for guiding the priorities and
    tasks of the development team. Likewise, it can help users make a decision
    about whether the project is a good fit for their environments, rather
    than risking a wrong guess.</para>

    <para>However, you'll also notice that many of the reports we discussed
    overlap in functionality, or else provide total functional duplication.
    Obviously, providing all of these reports can actually muddy the waters,
    making it harder to make good decisions about the project. So, what
    reports should we use to assemble a killer report suite?</para>

    <para>The key is to get the right mix of metrics and other project
    information. In doing this, there is no absolute right answer as to which
    particular reports you should use; otherwise, it really wouldn't make
    sense to cover alternative reports that provide such similar
    functionality. Your project's environment may determine some of the
    answers (for instance, does your company have a Cenqua site license that
    would make Clover a natural choice?), and your preferences for data
    presentation may also provide some guidance. Whatever choices you make,
    you should try to include a complete snapshot of the metrics and other
    information that can help people make informed decisions. Some important
    metrics include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>test coverage and status (successes vs. failures)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>NCSS and other basic measurements of class size</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>metrics of class/package design quality</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>browsable source</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>API documentation</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>changelog for the project</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>backward compatibility information</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>potential problem areas in the source code</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Also, to give your users and developers convenient access to
    critical project infrastructure, you should also consider publishing the
    following project information:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>mailing list addresses</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>issue tracker URL</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>continuous integration URL</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>development team listing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>contributor listing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>project dependencies</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>source repository (especially if it's an open-source
        project)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>project license (again, especially if it's an open-source
        project)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>While there's not much point in having reports that overlap one
    another, it is important to include as much of these report types as you
    can. Publishing a comprehensive project website that includes the right
    mix of reports will give your user and developer communities a common
    rallying point, which helps to focus and enrich these communities.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-tips-tricks">
    <title>Tips and Tricks</title>

    <section id="reporting-sect-control-loc">
      <title>Control the Locations of Report Links in the Site Menu</title>

      <para>If you want to change the location of the Project Reports menu in
      your website navigation, you can refer to the entire menu with the
      following:</para>

      <screen>&lt;menu ref="reports"/&gt;
</screen>

      <para>Simply add this line to your site descriptor, in the desired
      position. When you regenerate the website, you should see the Project
      Reports menu move accordingly.</para>

      <para>If, on the other hand, you want to remove the Project Reports menu
      altogether, and move the reports it contains into other menus, you'll
      have to reference each report separately, according to their page
      location on the site. For example, if you wanted to move your project's
      JavaDocs into the Developers menu, you might have a menu entry like
      this:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Moving Reports Links in Site Menu</title>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;project name="Hello World"&gt;
  ...
  &lt;body&gt;
    ...
    &lt;menu name="Developers"&gt;
      ...
      &lt;item name="JavaDocs" href="/apidocs/index.html"/&gt;
    &lt;/menu&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</programlisting>
        </example></para>

      <note>
        <para>If you're not sure what href to use, generate the website with
        the Project Reports menu in place, and take notice of the link href
        generated for the report in question.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="reporting-sect-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>Project websites serve as a focal point for all activity surrounding
    a project. They house documentation, providing links to other project
    infrastructure, attract new community members, and help the project team
    to organize their plans. In open-source projects -- and increasingly, in
    the field of commercial software development as well -- this focal point
    is particularly important, since the development team can be widely
    dispersed in terms of both geography and time (time-zone differences can
    be much more difficult to overcome than geographical ones).</para>

    <para>In this chapter, we've talked about many different reports that
    Maven offers for the project website, in addition to discussing the ways
    that Maven reports are configured. We've discussed how reporting can offer
    a valuable counter-balance to the documentation commonly found on project
    websites, and deliver the information your users need to make decisions
    about integrating your project into their own environments. In addition,
    we've talked about how the right reports can help developers identify
    targets for improving existing project code, and plan for future
    development.</para>

    <para>This chapter is meant to provide the second half of the
    project-website story; for the first part, which shows you how to publish
    project documentation and configure the website using Maven, see the Site
    Generation chapter.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
